<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise, touching the libertie of a Christian. Written in Latin by Doctor Martine Luther. And translated into English by Iames Bell</title>
            <title>Von der Freiheit eines Christenmenschen. English</title>
            <author>Luther, Martin, 1483-1546.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1579</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 144 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 63 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06524</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16996</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108948</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844600</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844600</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9429</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06524)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9429)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 429:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise, touching the libertie of a Christian. Written in Latin by Doctor Martine Luther. And translated into English by Iames Bell</title>
                  <title>Von der Freiheit eines Christenmenschen. English</title>
                  <author>Luther, Martin, 1483-1546.</author>
                  <author>Bell, James, fl. 1551-1596.</author>
                  <author>Leo X, Pope, 1475-1521.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32], 92, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Ralph Newbery and H. Bynneman,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1579.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of a Latin version of: Von der Freiheit eines Christenmenschen.</note>
                  <note>Includes a letter to Pope Leo X dated Wittenberg, 6 Sept. 1520.</note>
                  <note>Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: A-H.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9429:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9429:1"/>
            <p>A Treatiſe, Touching the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written in Latin</hi> by Doctor Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine Luther.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And Tranſlated</hi> into Engliſh by IAMES BELL.</p>
            <p>At LONDON, Imprinted by Ralph New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery and H. Bynneman.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1579.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9429:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9429:2"/>
            <head>To the right Honourable, and moſt vertuous Lady, <hi>Anne,</hi> Counteſſe of War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter I had finiſhed this ſimple Tranſlation for the behoofe of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lettered, ſome of my welwillers conceiuing well of the matter, were very deſirous that I ſhould preſent the ſame to ſome noble perſonage: others challenging more knowledge in Courtly affaires, perſwaded the contrary, being of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that though it might in ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect ſeeme plauſible enough, yet the preſent being but ſimple, could not deſerue to be aduanced to Court, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to place of eſtate. And although I ſuppoſed, and partly knew, that the opinion of the later was but weake in
<pb facs="tcp:9429:3"/>
iudgement: yet loe, it made ſo much the longer ſtay in deliberation, by how much I was abaſhed in conceit, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of my rudeneſſe, and vnaptneſſe, to ſatisfie the learned, &amp; Courtly eares. Neuertheleſſe, hauing clothed my Stranger in Engliſh attyre (whom I call a Stranger, in reſpect of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, who was the firſt Author therof.) And well knowing the Court, to the great fame and honour thereof, by the ſpace of many yeares now paſſed, to haue bin the reſcue of all Strangers di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed, I could not but beleeue, that in the Court, this Stranger ſo godly, ſo zealous, ſo learned, ſhould be both ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily accepted, and gently entertained: and encouraged by this well knowne experience, I yeelded my ſelfe to the firſt perſwaſion, and finding by gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall report (Madame) the noble orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and gifts, I ſpeake not onely of
<pb facs="tcp:9429:3"/>
nature, but of godlineſſe, wiſedome, and zeale, ioyned with ſingular milde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and benignity, being the fruits of grace amongſt the reſt eſpecially, to ſhine in your ſacred breaſt, I was ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by emboldned to proceede, and aboue all others, to preſume vpon your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable patience, and to preſent to your honour this my poore Stranger: In whoſe commendation I dare bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirme, that there was neuer any a more truſty ſeruant to his Maſter: ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer any of more vndaunted courage in his Maſters cauſe: neuer any that aduentured, or durſt aduenture far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: neuer any that vſed more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie, magnanimity, and force, in battering the fortreſſes of the enemy: neuer any that pierced deeper, preuai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led further, and procured larger, for the ſafety of poore Chriſtians, ſo many hundred yeares oppreſſed, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned,
<pb facs="tcp:9429:4"/>
impoueriſhed, yoked, and chained in miſerable captiuitie, through the monſtrous outrage of that execrable Nimrod of Rome, amongſt many of whoſe exployts, albeit there cannot any one bee found, that is not able to repleniſh the Spirituall and true Chriſtian man, with ſuch, and ſo great ioy, as can not with my penne be expreſſed, yet in my ſimple iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, this one little treatiſe of his, which I haue now aboue all others ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected to tranſlate, doth farre excell and ſurmount in ghoſtly conſolation, wherein are entreated no vaine, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh, or trifling toyes, but ſweet, dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctable, ſerious, weighty, and matters of great importance, namely, the pure faith of a true Chriſtian man, the ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnion and marriage of the moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miable Bridegrome IESV Chriſt, to the poore miſerable abiect and
<pb facs="tcp:9429:4"/>
wretched Soule, the well ordering of chriſtian life, and the gladſome chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian freedome and liberty. Euen ſuch a one is this my Stranger, whom, if it may pleaſe your Honour to vouchſafe vnto your honourable patronage, I ſhall not onely accompt my ſelfe moſt happy in my ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, but alſo (acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging your honourable courteſie in full ſatisfaction of mine Engliſh coſt, ſuch as it is employed) yeeld my ſelfe doubly bounden &amp; indebted to your Honour in any thing which my penne may endeauour, or trauell may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme. The holy ghoſt, the Author of all goodneſſe, &amp; ghoſtly conſolation, repleniſh your heart with the moſt ioyfull freedome of his grace, to the comfort of all ſuch as trauell in the building of Gods holy temple.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your honours moſt humble at commandement, <hi>IAMES BELL.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9429:5"/>
            <head>¶ To <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth, Biſhop of <hi>Rome, Martyne Luther</hi> ſendeth greeting in Chriſt Ieſu our Lord.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt the monſters of this world, with whom I haue bin in continuall combate theſe three whole yeeres and more, I am enforced now at the length to turne mine eyes vnto you, and to haue you in remembrance (O moſt holy father <hi>Leo</hi>) yea, for as much as you only bee accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the very cauſe of this my turmoyle, I cannot chooſe but bee alwayes mindfull of you. And albeit I haue beene conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, through inſatiable cruelty of your wicked Sicophants, raging againſt mee without deſert, to appeale to the next ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Counſell, little eſteeming the moſt vaine decrees of your predeceſſours, <hi>Pius,</hi> and <hi>Iulius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees doe prohibite to appeale to the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councels.</note> who of a fooliſh tyranny haue prohibited ſuch appellatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be made fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the See Apoſtolique. Yet did I neuer meane whiles ſo eſtrange mine affection from your holines, but that I haue with all mine heart wiſhed all felicity and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines
<pb facs="tcp:9429:5"/>
to you and to your See, and in my daily prayers with teares and ſighes, euen to the vttermoſt of my power, haue hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſought God for the ſame: But as for thoſe which haue hitherto practiſed to ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rify me with the authority and maieſty of your name, I haue now begun almoſt to contemne and account them of no force: onely one thing yet remayneth, which I may not deſpiſe, which occaſioned mee at this preſent to addreſſe my letters to your holineſſe. And this it is,<note place="margin">The cauſe why Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wrote theſe Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to the Pope.</note> becauſe I perceiue that I am accuſed vnto your holineſſe, and very grievouſly blamed for my raſhneſſe, in that I am ſuppoſed to haue no conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of your perſonage.</p>
            <p>Wherein, to confeſſe the truth plainly, I am priuy in mine owne conſcience, that whereſoeuer behooueth me to make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your of perſon, I did neuer ſpeak ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of without all honour and reuerence: the contrary wherof if I had attempted at any time, I might not haue beene able to iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, and would by all meanes poſſible haue ſubſcribed vnto their iudgments, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiued of me herein, and withall would haue ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed
<pb facs="tcp:9429:6"/>
to nothing more willingly, than to make open recantation of this my teme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and miſdemeanour in that behalfe: I haue named you a <hi>Daniel</hi> in <hi>Babylon:</hi>
               <note place="margin">How Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wards the Pope.</note> and your notable innocency with how earneſt affection I haue defended againſt your ſlanderous enemy <hi>Sylueſter,</hi> euery reader doth ſufficiently vnderſtand, namely, that the opinion and report of your vnrepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uable life, reſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding in each coaſt through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole world, by the teſtimony of ſo many &amp; ſo notable perſonages is m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re famous and renoumed, than that it may be impeached by the ſiniſter practiſe of any man, though neuer ſo great a potentate. I am not ſo void of reaſon, as to defame him whom all men commend, ſo alſo haue I beene euer of this minde, not to ſeeke the defacing of any one, though otherwiſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous by report of al others for I reioyce not at another mans blemiſh, who am my ſelf a ſufficient witnes to mine own conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, of mine owne great beame in mine owne eye: nor can be the firſt that may caſt a ſtone at the woman taken in adultery.</p>
            <p>Indeed I haue accuſtomed my ſelfe to
<pb facs="tcp:9429:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
inueigh againſt wicked doctrines,<note place="margin">Why Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was ſo vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his aduerſaries</note> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſharply: and haue pinched mine ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, not for their licentious liues, but for their irreligious doctrines, ſomewhat earneſtly: whereof it ſo little repenteth me, that I am fully perſwaded, without all regard had of mens cenſures herein, to perſeuere in that vehemency of zeale: en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced hereunto by the example of Chriſt, who according to the ſame zeale, ſpared not to call his aduerſaries Vipers brood, blinde Hypocrites, and children of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill. So doth Paul accuſe <hi>Symon Magus</hi> to bee the child of Sathan, full of fraud and malice.<note place="margin">Paul and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets be ſharpe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings.</note> And ſome others he repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth openly by the name of Dogges, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuers, and crafty Simoniſts. Of whoſe ſharpe words, if nice delicates may bee admitted Iudges, nothing ſhall bee ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed more nipping and vnciuill. What can bee more vehement than the Prophets? certes the manners of our age,<note place="margin">The deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of our age.</note> are become ſo tender through the furious ſwarme of clawbacks, that wee can no ſooner feele our ſoares a little diſcouered, but wee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime forthwith that we are launced: and
<pb facs="tcp:9429:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
being not able to crack the credit of the truth by any cauillation, we flee from her, condemning her of curriſhneſſe, impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and modeſty. How ſhall ſalt ſeaſon if it be not ſauory? what auaileth the edge of a ſword if it cannot cut? curſed is the man that doth the Lords worke fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently. Wherefore I humbly beſeech you (my reuerend <hi>Leo</hi>) vouchſafe theſe my let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters for mine excuſe, and withall perſwade your ſelfe, that I neuer conceiued any e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill of your perſonage. Then alſo, that I am ſo affected towards you, as that I could heartily wiſh vnto your Holineſſe all feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city for euer.<note place="margin">Luthers variance.</note> Moreouer, that I am not at variance with any man, for conuerſation of life, but only touching the only word of truth. In all matters elſe whatſoeuer, I will giue place to others, but the word, neither can I, nor will I forſake or deny. Who ſo that iudgeth of mee otherwiſe, or hath conceiued otherwiſe of my writings, doth not iudge truly, nor conceiue thereof a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Court of Rome.</note>But your See (which is tearmed the Court of Rome, and which neither
<pb facs="tcp:9429:7"/>
you, nor any man liuing can deny to bee more filthy than Babylon and Zodome, and as farre forth as I can conceiue, growne to moſt lamentable, forlorne, and moſt ſhameleſſe impiety) I haue deteſted indeed, and haue taken it very grieuouſly, that the people of Chriſt ſhould be deluded vnder the countenance of your name and your holineſſe, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pretence of the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> and herein haue reſiſted, and will reſiſt the ſame, as long as the ſpirit of Faith ſhall liue in me: not becauſe I dare thinke to atchieue impoſſibilities, or that by mine onely endeauour, I may hope for any amendment in this moſt confuſely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered <hi>Babylon,</hi> being circumuented with ſuch a rable of brainſicke blaunchers: But becauſe I do acknowledge my ſelfe indebted to my poore brethren, whoſe ſafety I ought to regard; that the loſſe of them that periſh may bee abridged, or at the leaſt leſſe infection may ſpreade a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad from thoſe Romiſh botches.<note place="margin">What ſtuffe hath iſſued from Rome into the world.</note> For theſe many yeeres now <hi>Rome</hi> hath ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded the whole world with nothing
<pb facs="tcp:9429:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
elſe, (whereof your holines is not ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t) but with vtter deſtruction of all things, of bodies, of ſoules, and with moſt peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferous patterns of al moſtrous wickednes: which doth rage at this day in the ſight of all men, more manifeſt than the Sun in midday:<note place="margin">The Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </note> And the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> which was ſometime the moſt holy of all other, is become the moſt licentious denne of theeues, the moſt ſhameleſſe Brothelhouſe of all the world, the kingdome of Sinne, Death, and Hell, in ſo much that it paſſeth all reach of man to deuiſe any abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that is not haunted there, no though Antichriſt himſelfe were come.</p>
            <p>In the meane time you (right reuerend father <hi>Leo</hi>) ſit as a Lambe in the middeſt of Wolues, as <hi>Daniel</hi> a middeſt the Lions, and are with <hi>Ezechiel</hi> conuerſant with Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions. How can you alone be able to w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand all theſe monſters? Gard your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage with three or foure Cardinals ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent in all learning, and moſt vertuous in manners: what ſhall this handfull doe amongſt ſo great a troupe? you ſhall all be ſooner ſwallowed vp with poyſon, before
<pb facs="tcp:9429:8"/>
you may dare attempt any reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The Court of <hi>Rome</hi> is vtterly vndone, the wrath of God is bent againſt it euen for euer and euer. It hateth counſels, it feareth to bee reformed, it is not able to reſtraine the furiouſneſſe of her impiety: and it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſheth the prophecy of her mother, of whom it is written on this wiſe: Wee haue cheriſhed <hi>Babylon,</hi> and ſhe is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered, let vs forſake her. Indeed it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to you, &amp; your Cardinals, to haue cured thoſe plagues: but this gout ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the Phyſitians drugges, and this cart will not goe driuen nor led. Moued there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with remorſe, herein I ſorrowed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes (right reuerend <hi>Leo</hi>) becauſe you were enſtalled Pope in this wicked age, whoſe worthineſſe deſerued a better time: For the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> is not worthy to be poſſeſſed of you, and ſuch as you are, but rather of Sathan himſelfe,<note place="margin">Sathan raighneth at Rome, not the Pope.</note> which in truth doth raigne in this <hi>Babylon,</hi> more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you. O would to God you could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent you ſelfe rather with ſome priuate benefice, or with your parents patrimony, renouncing this portlineſſe, wherewith
<pb facs="tcp:9429:9"/>
thoſe flatterers your moſt deteſtable ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, doe vaunt you to bee glorious, with which glory none are meet to bee glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, but trayterous Iſcariots, the impes of perdition. For what commendation elſe do you get in that Palace (my <hi>Leo</hi>) but that by how much any Teacher is more wicked execrable, ſo much the more ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hee may ſhrowd him vnder your name and authority, to robbe men of their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and ſoules, to heape miſchiefe vpon miſchief, to oppreſſe Faith, Truth, together withall the Church of God? Oh moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate <hi>Leo,</hi> doubtleſſe enthronized in a moſt perilous place of renowne:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eugenius</hi> was Pope, ſometimes Schollar vnto <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard.</hi>
               </note> for I tell you the truth, becauſe I doe wiſh well vnto you: For if <hi>Bernard</hi> took compaſſion of his welbeloued <hi>Eugenius,</hi> when as yet there was ſome better hope of the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> (though then alſo it was filthily em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perious,) whereof may we complaine firſt, who haue weltered theſe three hundred yeeres now in ſtench and deſtruction? Is not this true, that vnder the whole out-ſtretched face of the heauens, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tagious, more peſtiferous, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:9429:9"/>
more odious, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the court of <hi>Rome?</hi> for it is more incomparably execrable, than the turkiſh impiety, ſo that true it is indeed, that the ſame which was in times paſt the gate of heauen, is now become a certaine gaping gulfe of Hell, and ſo vnſatiable a gulfe, as cannot poſſibly be ſatisfied, the wrath of God being fully bent againſt the ſame.<note place="margin">One only remedy remaining in the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church.</note> One only comfort remaineth for the poore wretches, if we be able to reclaime &amp; preſerue ſome few at the leaſt, from this wide gaping iawes (as I ſaid before,) Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold (my holy father <hi>Leo</hi>) by what induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; by what reaſon I haue inueigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt this chaire of peſtilence: for it is ſo farre off from my thought to grow in outrage againſt your perſonage, as that I would hope to obtaine your fauour, and bee deemed a ſtout patrone of your ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, if I would manfully, and valiantly cruſh in pieces the Gates of this your dungeon, or of this your Hell rather: for howſoeuer the generall force of all polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie can poſſibly imagine to worke the vtter ruine of the moſt horrible Court of this age, the ſame ſhall redound al to your
<pb facs="tcp:9429:10"/>
perſon, to the preſeruation of your eſtate, and to the ſafety of many others together with you. Such as doe worke her confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, doe execute your function. They do aduance the glory of Chriſt, which doe by all meanes poſſible deteſt her. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, they be right Chriſtians which are leaſt Romaniſts.</p>
            <p>But to ſpeake hereof more at large. There neuer came any ſuch thought into my head, as to enueigh againſt the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> or to diſcourſe thereof any thing at all: For when I perceiued that all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruatiues were medicinable to procure her amendment, I withdrew mee from her, and deliuering her a libell of diuorce, I ſpake vnto her in this wiſe: Hee that is filthy, let him continue in his filthineſſe ſtill, and he that is vncleane, let him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in his vncleaneſſe ſtill, yeelding my ſelfe ouer to the calme and quiet ſtudy of holy Scriptures, whereby I might be able to profit my brethren dwelling round about me. Here now when as I could ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry little auaile, Sathan beganne to open his eyes, and to prick forward his truſty
<pb facs="tcp:9429:10"/>
ſeruant <hi>Iohn Eccius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Who did prouoke Luther to purſue the trecheries of the falſe deceiuers.</note> a notorious enemy of Chriſt, ſwelling with a certaine outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious licenciouſneſſe of glory, chalenging me to a combate vnloked for, tripping me for one very little word eſcaped mee vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares, touching the Supremacy of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> This ſame proud praun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing <hi>Thraſo,</hi> fruſhing in his Fuſtian fumes, vanted luſtily that hee durſt attempt all things for Gods glory, and the honour of the holy See Apoſtolique: And being puft vp with ſaucy malapertneſſe of abuſing your power, made no ſurer accompt of any thing, than of preſent conqueſt, ſeeking thereby not ſo much the pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy of Peters chayre, as his owne prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy peereleſſe amongſt all the Diuines of this age, for the better atchieuing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, hee perceiued that to leade poore LVTHER Captiue, would bee not the leaſt brauery of his triumph, which enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, becauſe it hapned vnluckily &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the exhortation of the fooliſh Sophiſter, the man waxed incredibly fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious: for he perceiued, that whatſoeuer infamy was rayſed by mee, againſt
<pb facs="tcp:9429:11"/>
the Romiſh Church, was procured by his owne onely temerity and raſhneſſe.</p>
            <p>Vouchſafe here I beſeech you (right re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend <hi>Leo</hi>) that I may here once defend mine owne cauſe, and diſcouer your very naturall enemies: It is not vnknowne vnto you, (I ſuppoſe) how your Legate the Cardinall of Saint <hi>Sixtus</hi> did deale with me,<note place="margin">Cardinall <hi>Caietane.</hi>
               </note> an vndiſcrete man, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciuill, nay rather a falſe man: Into whoſe protection when I had yeelded my ſelfe and all mine eſtate for the reuerence that I beare to your holineſſe, he endeauoured not to conclude a quietneſſe which hee might euen with halfe a word haue eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed eaſily, when as I then promiſed to keepe ſilence, and put vp my quarrell, ſo that mine aduerſaries might be inioyned to doe the like. But this glorious man, not ſatisfied with theſe conditions, began to authorize mine aduerſaries, to giue them free liberty, and to enioyne mee to recant, which was no parcell of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. Certeſſe, when here the cauſe was yet in very good plight, through his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate handling, it began to feſter
<pb facs="tcp:9429:11"/>
worſe &amp; worſe, wherupon, whatſoeuer fell afterwards, was to be imputed, not to <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> but to <hi>Caietanes</hi> vndiſcreteneſſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together, who would not permit mee to be ſilent, and to remaine in quiet, which I did at that time moſt earneſtly deſire, for what might I doe more?</p>
            <p>After him came <hi>Charles Militius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Charles Militius.</note> and he alſo Legate of your holineſſe, who trauel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling many and ſundry waies, poaſting here and there, forth and backe, and omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting nothing that might appertaine to the redreſſe of the ſtate of the cauſe, which <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ietane</hi> had raſhly and proudly diſordered, could ſcarce at the length bring it to paſſe, (though countenanced herein by the moſt renowned Prince <hi>Frederike</hi> the Elector) that he might haue once or twice ſome fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar conference with me,<note place="margin">Iudges of Luthers cauſe cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen.</note> where <hi>I</hi> once againe yeelded to your authoritie, conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to hold my peace, not refuſing either Archbiſhop of <hi>Tryers,</hi> or the Biſhop of <hi>Numburgh</hi> to be iudge in the cauſe, which was concluded and obtained. Whiles theſe matters proceeded thus very order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, behold the other, yea, a greater enemy
<pb facs="tcp:9429:12"/>
of your eſtate,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccius.</hi> The diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation at <hi>Lypſia.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Eccius</hi> ruſheth out with his diſputation at <hi>Lypſia,</hi> which hee had then publiſhed againſt <hi>D. Conolaſtadius,</hi> and picking a new quarrell of the ſupremacy of the Pope, bends his ſhot againſt mee at vnawares, and vtterly diſſolueth this concluſion of Peace. In the meane time <hi>Carolus Militius</hi> attendeth the ſucceſſe, Diſputation beginneth, Iudges are choſen: yet neuertheleſſe, hitherto nothing was determined, and no maruaile, foraſmuch as through <hi>Eccius</hi> falſe lying, diſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bling, &amp; falſe packing, all things were full of vnqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſſe, abounded in all melancholly, and fraught of all parts with confuſed diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ſo that which way ſoeuer Iudgement were giuen, greater ſtormes would be ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: for he ſought for Glory, and not for the Truth. And here alſo I omitted no part of duty that behooued me to doe.</p>
            <p>And I confeſſe, that this was not the leaſt occaſion of the diſcouery of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh trumperies: yet ſuch as it was, if any offence grew thereby, it was altogether to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> imputed to <hi>Eccius,</hi> which vndertaking <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> enterpriſe aboue his reach, whiles he
<pb facs="tcp:9429:12"/>
gaped ouer-greedily for his owne glory, did diſplay abroad to the view of the whole world, the infamous eſtate of <hi>Rome.</hi> This,<note place="margin">The flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer <hi>Ecci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> did hurt the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> more than the moſt mightieſt enemy elſe could doe.</note> euen this ſame <hi>Eccius</hi> is your e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy (my <hi>Leo</hi>) or rather the enemie of your Court, by whoſe onely example, a man may learne ſufficiently, that there is none more peſtilent an enemie, than a flatterer, for what gayned hee by his blaunching elſe but a miſchiefe, which no earthly King nor Potentate could bring to paſſe? for the name of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Court doth ſtincke now ouer the whole world, and the Papane au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie is very much craſed, notorious ignorance is generally cryed out vpon, whereof wee ſhould not haue heard any one word at all, if <hi>Eccius</hi> had not turmoyled the peace agreed vpon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Charles</hi> and mee, which now himſelfe perceiueth plaine enough, all too late, and in vaine, ſtorming a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the imprinting of my Bookes. Thus much behooued him then to haue thought vpon, when like a wilde vntamed Colt, hee raunged wholly for
<pb facs="tcp:9429:13"/>
glory, and when he ſought naught elſe but his owne aduancement, vnder the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of your holineſſe, to your maruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous detriment and danger; notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the fooliſh vaine man hoped, that I would haue ſurceaſed, and kept ſilence, being afraid of the ſound of your autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity (for of his wit and learning, I doe not beleeue, that he was ſo foole-hardie) and now perceiuing that I haue taken courage, and my writings ſcattered abroad too much, being all too late ſory for his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduiſed wilfulneſſe, he doth vnderſtand, that there raigneth one in Heauen, who reſiſteth the proud, and caſteth downe the haughty of minde, if at leaſt yet hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue ſo much.</p>
            <p>Therefore, when as by this our diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, nothing was wrought but a greater confuſion of the Romiſh cauſe, <hi>Charles Militius</hi> maketh now his third repaire to the elders of the order, being aſſembled in the Chapter houſe, deſireth aduiſe how to qualifie the contention, which was euen now growne to great trouble, and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull perill: from whom (for as much as
<pb facs="tcp:9429:13"/>
there was ſmall hope now to ouerthrow me, Gods mercy aſſiſting me) ſome of the greateſt peſonages were ſent vnto me, to intreate, that I would haue conſideration of the eſtimation and honour of your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and that I ſhould in humble let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, excuſe both your innocency, and mine owne, declaring that the matter was not yet growne to ſo deſpaired a caſe, as to be without hope of recouery, if <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth would of his naturall inclination to lenitie, vouchſafe his ayde thereto; here now as one that hath alwaies both offered, and wiſhed for tranquility, that I may the better apply my ſelfe to more quiet, and more profitable exerciſe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as I had ſo vehemently turmoyled my ſelfe to this end, that in mightineſſe and force, as well of words, as courage, I might ſuppreſſe the inſolencie of them, whom I perceiued to be farre vnequall to match with me, I did not only yeeld wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, but with ioy alſo and thankefull minde, imbraced the requeſt, as a moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable benefit, if it may proue according to our expectation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:9429:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <note place="margin">Luther will not recall any thing.</note>In this minde I come now (oh holy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) and falling proſtrate at your feet, doe moſt humbly beſeech you to grant your aſſiſtance herein, and to reſtraine (if it bee poſſible) the outrage of theſe flatterers, the very cankers of Vnity, though masking vnder the vizor of peace. But to wiſh mee to reuoke that which I haue written (moſt holy father) it booteth not for any man to hope for, vnleſſe he be deſirous rather to haue the matter to be more largely blown abroad.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">He will not ſuffer the theeues to make lawes for interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Gods word.</note>Moreouer, I doe not allow theſe lawes concerning the interpretation of Gods word to be reſtrained to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or tyed to any place, for as much as the word of God (which teacheth free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of all things elſe) ought not to bee ſtraighted, and abridged of her freedome. The two conditions reſerued, there is elſe nothing but that I can both doe, and ſuffer: yea, will moſt willingly yeeld vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: I doe late hate contention: I will chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge no man, and I will not bee challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged againe, but if I be teazed, I will not hold my tongue in my maſter Chriſt his
<pb facs="tcp:9429:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
behalfe, for it is an eaſie matter for your holineſſe to command ſilence, and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſſe on both parts, the quarrels being ſummoned before you, and determined, which I haue alwaies deſired earneſtly to heare.</p>
            <p>Beware therefore (my holy father <hi>Leo</hi>) that you hearken not to theſe enchanters,<note place="margin">He coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celleth the Pope not to he are flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers.</note> which make you not a naturall man, but halfe a God, and would enduce you to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that ye are able to command, and exact whatſoeuer you liſt. It will not be ſo, neither ſhall you preuaile, you are the ſeruant of ſeruants, and placed in the moſt dangerous eſtate of all others. Let them not beguile you, which imagine you to be the Lord of the World, which will not permit any man to be a Chriſtian man; vnleſſe he be ſubiect to your authoritie, which doe chatter and iangle, that you are of power to command in Heauen, in Hell, and in Purgatory. Thoſe, euen thoſe be your enemies, and ſeek the deſtruction of your ſoule, as the Prophet Eſay doth witneſſe, O my good people, ſuch as doe praiſe thee, euen thoſe doe deceiue thee.
<pb facs="tcp:9429:15"/>
They are out of the way, which doe extoll your maieſtie aboue the Councell and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſal Church. They are out of the way which doe inueſt you onely in the right of interp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing Scriptures, for ſuch doe pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe to eſtabliſh in the Church all their owne impieties, vnder your name. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las for woe, by the meanes of thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Sathan hath preuailed much in your predeceſſors. To be briefe, beleeue none of them that doe magnifie you, but ſuch as do humble you, for this is the iudgement of God, <hi>He hath throwne downe the mighty from their ſeate, and hath exalted the humble and meeke.</hi> Behold what inequality there is betwixt Chriſt and his ſucceſſors, when as they all notwithſtanding will be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Vicars of Chriſt. And I feare much, leſt many of them be his Vicares in deede a great deale too earneſtly: for a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car is hee that doth preſent the perſon of his Prince being not in place.<note place="margin">What a Vicar is.</note> Now, if the Pope doe beare dominion whiles Chriſt is not preſent, nor reſiant within his heart, what is he elſe, than the Vicar of Chriſt? But what manner of Church is that then
<pb facs="tcp:9429:15"/>
elſe, but a rude multitude without Chriſt? And what maner of Vicar is this elſe, but <hi>Antechriſt,</hi> and an Idol? How much more truly ſpake the Apoſtles, who named them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues the ſeruants of Chriſt being preſent, and not Vicars of Chriſt being abſent.</p>
            <p>Peraduenture, I ſhall be accounted a ſhameleſſe fellow, that dare preſume to teach ſo mighty a potentate, from whom all others ought to be inſtructed, and from whom all iudiciall Courts ought to fetch definitiue ſentence (as your peſtiferous clawbackes doe arrogantly vaunt) but I follow the example of <hi>Bernard,</hi> in his Book entituled <hi>De co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideratione ad Eugeniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> a neceſſary Booke for all Popes to know by heart. Neither doe I take this vpon me of any greedy deſire to teach, but of duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full affection, in a pure and faithfull zeale, which doth enforce vs to be afraid, euen of the moſt plauſible things in our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours: and being altogether exerciſed in the perils and profits of other men, will not admit any reſpect to bee had of the worthy or vnworthy: for in as much at I know, that your holineſſe is troubled,
<pb facs="tcp:9429:16"/>
and toſſed at <hi>Rome,</hi> that is to ſay, in the maine ſea of all ſides enuironed about with infinite dangers, and that you ſwimme now in ſuccourleſſe waues miſerably, as that you ſtand in neede of the meaneſt helpe of any your pooreſt brethren: I iudged it a point of no great abſurditie, if I did lay aſide the remembrance of your maieſtie for a time, vntill I had executed the dutie of Loue. I will not flatter in ſo weighty and perillous a cauſe: in which doing, if I be not conceiued to be moſt friendly, and moſt humble vnto you, there is one that doth conceiue and iudge.</p>
            <p>To conclude, becauſe I would not ſeeme to come empty handed vnto your holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, I bring with me this little Treatiſe, publiſhed vnder your name, as a pledge of truce to be concluded, &amp; of good ſucceſſe: wherein you may ſomewhat conceiue in what kinde of ſtudies I can, and am very deſirous to employ my time, more fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and commodiouſly: if I heretofore might, or hereafter may now conuenient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be free from your wicked flatterers. The matter is ſmall, if you regard the outward
<pb facs="tcp:9429:16"/>
coate, but if you comprehend the thing is ſelfe, it is (if I be not deceiued) a moſt nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble patterne of a Chriſtian life, briefly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piled. Neither haue I ought elſe being a poor man to gratifie your holineſſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, neither neede you any other preſent, than ſpirituall conſolation wherewithall I doe recommend my ſelfe wholly to your fatherhood, &amp; holineſſe. Which I beſeech Chriſt Ieſu to preſerue for euer. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>At Wittenberge <date>the ſixt of September, in the yeere of our Lord, <hi>1520.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:9429:17"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:9429:17"/>
            <head>¶ A Treatiſe of Martyne Luther touching Chriſtian liberty.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Any men haue beene of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion that Chriſtian faith is an eaſie matter, yea of them alſo not a few haue accompted it in the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Vertues, euen as a companion of vertue it ſelf. And this haue they done, becauſe they haue had no tryall thereof by any proofe, nor haue at any time taſted of what force &amp; power it is: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it cannot be poſſible that any man may bée able to write pithily, or vnderſtand effectually the things that are written concerning the ſame truly, vnleſſe being pinched at ſome one time or another with ſome croſſe of tribulation, he hath felt the inward ſpirit thereof: But who ſo hath had but a meane taſte of the ſame, can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer poſſibly bee ſatisfied with writing, ſpeaking, thinking, and hearing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. <hi>For it is a liuely ſpring vnto euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:9429:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 4.</note> according as Chriſt calleth it in the fourth of Iohn. Wherein my ſelfe, albeit I make no vaunt of my ſtore, and withall doe acknowledge the weakneſſe of mine imbecillity, yet doe neuertheleſſe truſt, that by meanes of ſundry and gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous temptations wherewith I haue bin turmoyled, I haue attained no ſmall dramme of Faith. And that I am there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of able to treat (though not ſo eloquent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet certes more ſubſtantially) than thoſe literall and ouer ſubtill ſchoolemen haue hitherto yet diſputed, as men altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ignorant in the things which them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues haue written. To the end therfore I may diſcouer a more eaſie way to the vnlettered to wade herein (to whoſe capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities I doe only apply my ſelfe) I doe ſet downe firſt theſe two propoſitions touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fréedome and bondage of the ſpirit.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <note place="margin">The po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions.</note>
                  <hi>1 <hi>A Chriſtian man is a moſt free Lord of all, ſubiect to none.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2 <hi>A Chriſtian man is a moſt dutifull ſeruant of all, ſubiect to all.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:9429:18"/>Although theſe two propoſitions ſo me to be méere contraries, yet when they ſhall be found to haue in them a certaine ſwéet agréement, they will auaile very much for our preſent purpoſe. For Saint <hi>Paul</hi> is the Author of them both, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in his firſt Epiſtle to the Corinths the twelfth Chapter, <hi>Being otherwiſe free,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.</note> 
               <hi>I made my ſelfe ſeruant of all.</hi> And in the thirteenth to the Romans.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.</note> 
               <hi>Owe nothing to any man, but that ye loue one another.</hi> But loue is naturally dutifull, and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly obedient to the thing that is loued, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo Chriſt, though Lord of all, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing borne of a woman, was made vnder the law, both frée altogether, and a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, at one ſelfe time in the ſhape of God, and in the ſhape of a ſeruant.</p>
            <p>Let vs enter into ſome higher &amp; more déepe conſideration of thoſe ſayings. Man doth conſiſt of two natures, to wit, ſpirituall, and corporall. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the ſpirituall nature (which ſome doe tearme to be the ſoule) hee is called ſpirituall, inward, and of the new man: In reſpect of the corporall (which
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:9429:19"/>
ſome call the fleſh) hee is called the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, outward, and the old man. Of the which the Apoſtle in the ſecond to the Corinthians,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor</hi> 4.</note> the fourth Chapter. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though our outward man be corruptible, yet our inward man is renued day by day.</hi> So that it commeth to paſſe through this diuerſity, that in the Scriptures two con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries are affirmed of one ſelfe ſame man, becauſe that theſe two men being within the ſame one man, doe kéepe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall battayle againſt each other, <hi>Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt the fleſh doeth couet againſt the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gala.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>and the ſpirit againſt the fleſh,</hi> as in the Epiſtle to the Galathians the fift Chapter.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">In what things Chriſtian liberty.</note>Firſt therefore let vs examine the inward man, and ſée by what reaſon hée may bée made iuſt, frée, and a true Chriſtian, that is to ſay, ſpirituall, new, and an inward man. And it is certaine, that no externall thing at all (how glorious title ſoeuer it beare) is in any reſpect auayleable to the attay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Chriſtian righteouſneſſe, or frée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, as neyther of any value to the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:9429:19"/>
procuring of vnryghteouſneſſe or bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, which is prooued by a very eaſie demonſtration. For what auayleth it to the ſoule, if the body bee in good ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, health, and full of life: If it eate, drinke, and doe fréely what it liſteth, when as euen the moſt wicked abiectes, bondeſlaues of all miſchiefe, doe enioy the ſame? Againe, what loſſe doeth the ſoule ſuſtaine by ſickneſſe, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, ſcarſitie of foode, thirſt, or by any other externall diſaduantage, when as the very reprobate, &amp; ſuch as be cleare voyde of all good conſcience, are moleſted with the ſame. None of all thoſe externall caſualties doe extende to the fréedome, or bondage, of the ſoule. In like manner it ſhall bee to ſmall pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, if the body bee garniſhed with gay Coapes, ſuch as Prieſts doe weare, or bee conuerſant in holy ſanctuaries, or bee exerciſed in holy Maſſe and Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens, or if it pray. faſt, abſtaine from certaine meats, or doe inure it ſelfe to what ſo euer exerciſe wrought and poſſible to be wrought by the body and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:9429:20"/>
in the body. To the fréedome and righteouſneſſe of the ſoule is requiſite matter of farre greater importance, whereas thoſe externall things afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, may happen vnto the moſt wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, by practiſing of the which, they become no better than plaine hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites. Contrariwiſe, it ſhall nothing preiudice the ſoule, to haue the body clad with vnhallowed garments, to frequent prophane places, to eat and drinke of all ſorts of meat without choiſe, not to bleat out prayer by note, yea to paſſe ouer all thoſe works aforeſaid, which may bée performed by the very Hipocrites.</p>
            <p>Bee it alſo that wee reiect all things, yea, euen ſpeculations, meditations, and whatſoeuer may bee done by the endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of the ſoule, it profiteth nothing. One thing,<note place="margin">Gods word ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the ſoule.</note> yea and that onely and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone is néedfull to the attainment of life, righteouſneſſe, and Chriſtian li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, which is the ſacred word of GOD the Goſpell of Ieſu Chriſt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Teſtimony of Chriſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:9429:20"/>
himſelfe in the eleuenth Chapter of Iohn. <hi>I am the reſurrection and life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>hee that beleeueth im me, ſhall not dye for euer.</hi> And in the eighth Chapter of Iohn. <hi>If the Sonne make you free,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.</note> 
               <hi>you ſhall bee truly free.</hi> And in the fourth Chapter of Mathew.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>Man liueth not by bread only, but by euery word that proceedeth out of the mouth of God.</hi> Let vs therefore take this for a ſtrong and an vndoubted Bulwarke, that the ſoule may want all things except the word of GOD, without the which nothing in the world can preſerue her in ſafety: But hauing the word, ſhee is rich, deſtitute of nothing, for as much as the word of GOD is the word of life, of light, of peace, righteouſneſſe, ſaluation, ioy, frée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, wiſdome, power, grace, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and ineſtimably the treaſure in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable of all goodneſſe. And this is it that mooued the Prophet in all his Octonary and in many other places,<note place="margin">Dauid.</note> with ſo many déepe ſighes and gronings to ſkriche out, and to call vpon the word
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:9429:21"/>
of God.<note place="margin">Famine of Gods word an horrible plague. Amos.</note> Againe, neither is there any more horrible a plague of Gods wrath, than whiles he ſendeth famine of hearing hys word. As he ſpeaketh in Amos: as neither is there any greater grace than if he ſpred abroad his word, as is ſpecified in the <hi>107</hi> Pſalm.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.</note> 
               <hi>He ſent his word, &amp; healed them, &amp; deliuered them from their deſtruction.</hi> Neither was Chriſt ſent to any other miniſtry, then the miniſtry of the word, nor is the Apoſtolicall Biſhopricke, and whole order Eccleſiaſticall, called and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted otherwiſe, than to the miniſtry of the word.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Which is the word of God.</note>But thou wilt demand, what word of God is this, and after what manner muſt it be vſed, conſidering there bee ſo many words of God? I anſwere, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle in the firſt to the Romanes doth expreſſe the ſame,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.</note> namely, the Goſpell of God concerning his ſonne incarnate, cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifyed, riſen againe, and glorified by the holy Ghoſt the ſanctifyer. For Chriſt hath preached, that is to ſay, hath fedde the ſoule, hath iuſtified, deliuered, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the ſoule, if ſhe beléeue his doctrine,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:9429:21"/>
for Fayth only is the ſafe and effectuall vſe of Gods word, as to the Romans the tenth. <hi>If thou confeſſe with thy mouth, and beleeue with the heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>that GOD hath rayſed him from the dead, thou ſhalt be ſaued.</hi> And againe, <hi>The end of the law is Chriſt, vnto righteouſneſſe to all them that doe beleeue.</hi> And to the Romans the firſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>The iuſt man ſhall liue by his owne faith,</hi> for the word of God cannot be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended and embraced by any workes, but by faith only. Euen ſo it is manifeſt, that as the Soule hath néed of the only word, to obtaine righteouſneſſe and life,<note place="margin">Faith only iuſtifieth.</note> euen ſo it is iuſtifyed by onely faith, and no workes; for if it might be iuſtifyed by any other meanes, then ſhould it not ſtande in néede of the word, and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently no néede of faith. But this faith cannot conſiſt altogether with workes, that is to ſay, if thou preſume to be iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed together with workes, whatſoeuer they be, for this were euen to halt on both legges, to worſhip <hi>Baal,</hi> and to kiſſe the hand, which of all other is abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, as witneſſeth <hi>Iob.</hi> Therefore,<note place="margin">Iob.</note>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:9429:22"/>
when thou beginneſt to beléeue, thou do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt learne withall, that all things in thée are altogether blameworthy, ſinfull, and damnable, according to that ſaying of the Apoſtle in the ſecond to the Romans,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>All haue ſinned, and haue need of the glory of God.</hi> And to the Romans, <hi>3. There is none that doth good, all haue declined out of the way, they are altogether become vnprofitable:</hi> for if thou know this once, thou ſhalt know that it is neceſſary for thée to hold faſt Chriſt, that beléeuing on him, who hath ſuffered for thee, and is riſen againe, thou maieſt be made ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man through this faith, being made frée from all thy Sinnes, and iuſtified by the merits of Ieſu Chriſt onely.</p>
            <p>Therefore, for as much as this fayth cannot beare dominion in any, but in the inward man, according to the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Paul in the tenth to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>With the heart we doe beleeue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to righteouſneſſe.</hi> And for as much as this faith only doth iuſtifie, it is euident that the inward man cannot in any wiſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:9429:22"/>
be iuſtified, made frée,<note place="margin">Man is not iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by any externall thing.</note> and ſaued by any externall worke or exerciſe, and that works whatſoeuer, auaile nothing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, as on the contrary through impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and only vnbeliefe of the heart, man is made guilty, and the bondſlaue of ſinne, and not by any externall ſinne or worke. And therefore the firſt and principall care of euery Chriſtian man ought to bée in this eſpecially, that ſetting aſide all vaine confidence of workes, hee ſtrengthen his faith more and more, and by daily increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings grow in knowledge, not of works, but of Chriſt Ieſu crucified for him, and riſen againe, as Peter in the laſt of his firſt Epiſtle teacheth, for as much,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> Pet. ult.</note> as none other worke doth make a true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man. So Chriſt in the ſixt of Iohn, when the Iewes aſked a queſtion what they ſhould doe to doe the works of God? excluding the multitude of works, wherewith he perceiued them to ſwell, and puft vp in pride, did preſcribe vnto them one only rule, ſaying, <hi>This is the worke of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 9.</note> 
               <hi>to beleeue on him whom he hath ſent, for him God the father hath
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:9429:23"/>
ſealed.</hi> From hence right faith in Chriſt duly procéeding,<note place="margin">Faith a treaſure in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable.</note> is a treaſure ineſtimable, contayning in it ſelfe all ſaluation, and preſeruing from all euill, as in the laſt of Marke,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.</note> 
               <hi>He that beleeueth and is baptiſed, ſhall be ſaued, he that beleeueth not, ſhall be damned,</hi> which treaſure Eſay inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly regarding, did in the tenth of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy ſay, The decréed conſumption o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerfloweth with righteouſneſſe, and the Lord of hoaſts ſhall perfectly fulfill the thing that he hath determined in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of the whole world, as if he had ſaid, Faith which is a briefe and ſummary fulneſſe of the Law, ſhall repleniſh the beléeuers with ſo great righteouſneſſe, that they ſhall not haue néed of any other helpe to attaine righteouſneſſe: and the ſame doth Paul teſtifie in the tenth to the Romanes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>For with the heart wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue vnto righteouſneſſe.</hi> But thou do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt aſke by what meanes it commeth to paſſe, that faith only may iuſtifie, &amp; giue ſuch a treaſure of ſo great goodneſſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out works, ſéeing that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole ſcriptures doe preſcribe vnto vs ſo many works,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:9429:23"/>
ſo many ceremonies, and ſo many lawes? I do anſwer, aboue all things be mindfull of this chiefely that hath bin ſpoken of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to wit, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> only faith without works doth iuſtifie, doth deliuer, and doth ſaue, which we will make more manifeſt here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. In the meane time ſeale vp this, that the whole Scripture of God is diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into two branches, namely,<note place="margin">The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures haue comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</note> comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements and promiſes. Indéed the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts do teach good things, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> things that are taught by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are not forthwith performed, for they do pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce what we ought to do, but do not giue power to doe the ſame, but are inſtituted to this end, to diſcouer man to himſelf, by meanes wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, man may know his own diſability to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the good, &amp; ſo deſpaire of his owne ſtrength: and for this cauſe they are called the old Teſtament, and ſo they be indéed. As for example, <hi>Thou ſhalt not couet,</hi> is a Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement, by the which we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinced all to be ſinners, becauſe man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not chooſe but couet, whatſoeuer his ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour be to the contrary, And therfore, that he may not couet, &amp; ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequently fulfil y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:9429:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement, he is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled to deſpaire of himſelfe, &amp; to ſéeke elſewhere for helpe of another, which he is not able to finde in himſelf,<note place="margin">Oſee.</note> as Oſee ſaith, <hi>Thy deſtruction co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of thy ſelfe, O Iſrael, &amp; thy health only fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">All the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements be equally impoſſible to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by vs.</note> The obſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of which one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement, is generall to be obſerued in all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt, for all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts are in all reſpects alike impoſſible vnto vs, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond our reach. Now when man is taught his own weakneſſe by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements, &amp; thereby brought into perplexity, how hee may be able to acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law, knowing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the law muſt be ſo of al parts acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſhed, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no one iot ſo much,<note place="margin">The Law muſt be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied.</note> or title thereof may be pretermitted, otherwiſe in danger of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall damnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> irrecouerable, being the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> truly humbled, and embaſed to nought in his owne eyes, he findeth nothing in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, whereby hee may bee iuſtified, and come to ſaluation. Loe, here commeth the other branch of the Scripture, namely, the promiſes of God, which doe bring the glad tidings of the glory of God, &amp; ſpeak on this wiſe. It thou wilt fulfill the Law, and not couet, as the Law requireth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:9429:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
here a remedy, Beleeue in Chriſt, in whom be promiſed vnto the, grace, righteouſneſſe, peace, fréedome, and in whom thou ſhalt haue all things if thou beléeue, and without whom thou ſhalt lack all things if thou doſt not beléeue, for that which is impoſſible to thée in all the works of the Law (which be many, and yet vnauayleable to ſaluation) thou ſhalt very eaſily,<note place="margin">We ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh all by faith.</note> and briefely atchieue and bring to paſſe through faith, becauſe God the father hath ſo eſtabliſhed all things in faith, that whoſoeuer haue faith, may poſſeſſe all things, and whoſoeuer lacketh faith, may poſſeſſe nothing,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>for God hath ſhut vp all things vnder vnbeleefe, that he might haue mercy on all.</hi>
               <note place="margin">God only comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth.</note> On this wiſe the promiſes of God doe giue fréely vnto vs, that which the commandements doe exact of vs perforce, and doe fullfill that, which the law doth ſtraitly command: that ſo all things may belong vnto God only, as well the commandements, as alſo the performance of the ſame. Onely God commandeth, only God performeth, and therefore Gods promiſes haue relation
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:9429:25"/>
to the new Teſtament, yea rather are the new Teſtament it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>For as much therefore as the promiſes of God be holy wordes, true, iuſt, peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and full of all goodneſſe, it commeth to paſſe,<note place="margin">The firſt arme of faith.</note> that the ſoule which doth cleaue ſtedfaſtly to the ſame, with an vnſhaken faith, is become ſo vnited vnto them, yea is alſo wholly ſo ſwallowed vp of them, that it doth not only partake thereof, but is throughly gorged, and made drunken with all the power and force of the ſame: for if the touching of Chriſt did giue health, how much more ſhall a very tender féeling of the word in the ſpirit? nay rather a through ſwallowing down of the word, communicate to the ſoule all things that appertaine to the word. By this meanes therefore, the Soule through faith onely without workes, beléeuing in the word of God, is iuſtified, ſanctified, pacifyed, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, and repleniſhed with all goodneſſe, and it is truly made the daughter of God, as it is ſaid in the firſt of Iohn, <hi>He gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> power to be made the ſonnes of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>euen them that doe beleeue in his name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:9429:25"/>By this it may be eaſily perceiued, from whence ſaith hath receiued ſo great force, and why neither any one, nor all good works are comparable vnto her, becauſe no worke can cleaue faſt vnto Gods word, nor be within the ſoule, wherin faith only, &amp; the word, do reigne &amp; gouern, for ſuch as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>word is, ſuch becommeth the ſoule, made by force of the word, euen as a fiery plate of iron doth glimmer like vnto fire, by meanes of vniting the fire and the plate together, ſo that it is manifeſt, that to a Chriſtian man faith ſufficeth only for all, and that he néedeth no works to bée iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by. Now if he néed no works, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo hée néeds not the law: if he haue no néed of the law, ſurely he is then frée from the law. So this alſo is true. The law is not made for the righteous man, and this is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame Chriſtian liberty. Our faith which doth worke in vs, not to be idlers, nor to giue our ſelues to luſt and euill life, but that wée bee not tyed to a neceſſity of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing the law, or doing works, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end to obtaine righteouſnes,<note place="margin">Another arme of faith.</note> or ſaluation ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by. Let this be the firſt arme of faith, &amp; let
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:9429:26"/>
vs ſée another, for this alſo is the duty of faith, that it reuerence him on whom it beleeueth, with a moſt godly and earneſt bent affection, to wit, that it accompt him true, &amp; worthy to be beléeued, for there is no honor like vnto the opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conceiued of truth and righteouſnes,<note place="margin">The grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt honor</note> wherewith we do moſt highly eſtéeme of him whom we doe beléeue, for what are we able to aſcribe to any perſon, more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> truth, righteouſnes, &amp; goodneſſe, of all parts perfect and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute? Contrariwiſe, it is a deteſtable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, to conceiue a ſecret opinion of a man to be falſe,<note place="margin">The grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach.</note> faithleſſe, and wicked. So the ſoule, as long as it beleeueth ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in God that maketh the promiſe, doth accompt him true &amp; righteous, than which opinion can nothing be more acceptable to God. This is the higheſt honor of God, to aſcribe vnto him truth, iuſtice, &amp; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer elſe ought to bee yeelded to him whom we doe beléeue: this man yeeldeth himſelfe ready to execute all his will: this man doth ſanctifie his name: this man ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth himſelfe to be exerciſed,<note place="margin">Perfect o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience.</note> according to the will &amp; pleaſure of God, becauſe clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:9429:26"/>
firmely to his promiſes, he doubteth not but that he is true, iuſt, wiſe, &amp; wil do, diſpoſe, and gouerne all things for the beſt: but is not ſuch a ſoule by the ſame his faith moſt humbly obedient to God in all things? what commandement remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth then, which this obedience hath not ſufficiently ſatisfied? what fulneſſe can be more abſolute, than all manner of humble obedience? but this obedience co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth not by workes, but by faith only, and belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the promiſes. On the other ſide, what Rebellion? what impiety?<note place="margin">Rebellion.</note> what greater reproach can there bee vnto God, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not to beléeue him whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he promiſeth? for what is this elſe, than either to make God a lier? or to be doubtfull of his truth? that is to ſay, to aſcribe truth to himſelfe, and to condemne God of vanity &amp; lying? wherein doth he not deny God, and make to himſelfe an image of himſelfe in his owne heart? what auayle déeds (I pray you) wrought in this vnbeléefe? though they ſéeme neuer ſo Angelicall, or Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall? And therefore very well did God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all, not in wrath &amp; luſt, but in vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:9429:27"/>
leſt ſuch as faine that they haue fulfilled the law through chaſte and méek works of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law (ſuch be vertues humane and ciuill) ſhould preſume vpon their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, when as being ſhut vp in the ſinne of vnbeleefe, they muſt either ſéeke for mercy, or to be damned through iuſtice. But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God doth ſée truth to be aſcribed vnto him,<note place="margin">God doth honour them that beleeue on him.</note> &amp; that he is worſhipped with the faith of our heart, which is as much honor as he deſireth, then doth hee honour vs againe, &amp; imputeth vnto vs truth &amp; righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes for this faithes ſake: for faith, in yelding to God his own, doth work truth &amp; righteouſnes, and therfore God doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence our righteouſnes again with glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, for it is true and iuſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God is true &amp; iuſt. So alſo, to aſcribe vnto God iuſtice &amp; truth, &amp; to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, is to be true and iuſt.<note place="margin">1 <hi>King</hi> 5.</note> To this effect we read in the <hi>1</hi> of the Kings, the <hi>5</hi> Chapter, <hi>Whoſoeuer doth honor me, I will glorify him: and whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer doth deſpiſe me, ſhal be naught ſet by.</hi> The ſame alſo pronounceth Paul to the Romans,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.</note> the <hi>4</hi> Chap. <hi>That to Abraham his owne faith was imputed vnto righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:9429:27"/>
becauſe through the ſame he gaue vnto God y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory moſt abſolutely, &amp; that if we beléeue, faith ſhal be imputed for the ſame cauſe vnto vs for righteouſnes. The third arme of faith,<note place="margin">The third arme of faith.</note> which is a iewell ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimable, is this, that it coupleth the ſoule with Chriſt, euen as the ſpouſe with her husband.<note place="margin">The vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the ſoule vnto her ſpouſe</note> By which ſacrament (as Paul <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eacheth) Chriſt &amp; the ſoule are made one fleſh. If they be one fleſh, then is there a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rue mariage betwixt them, yea, rather, a mariage of all other moſt perfect, abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>utely accompliſhed betwixt them (for the mariages betwixt man &amp; wife be but ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er figures of this vnion) whereupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oweth, that all things are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon betwixt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as well good as bad, ſo that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er Chriſt doth poſſeſſe, the faithfull ſoule may boldly preſume vpon the ſame, &amp; tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph ouer them, as though they were his own. Likewiſe, whatſoeuer appertaineth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the ſoule, the ſame may Chriſt chalenge vnto himſelfe, as if they were his owne. Let vs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare theſe together, &amp; wee ſhall perceiue ineſtimable treaſure. Chriſt is full of all grace, life, and ſauing health the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:9429:28"/>
ſoule is fraught full of all ſinne,<note place="margin">Behold in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable treaſures.</note> death, and damnation. Now let faith come betwixt theſe two, and it ſhall come to paſſe, that Chriſt ſhall be loaden with ſinne, with death, and with hell, but vnto the ſoule ſhall be imputed grace, life, and ſaluation, for it behooueth Chriſt, if hee bee the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, to accept, and ioyntly poſſeſſe the things appertaining to his ſpouſe, and withall, to communicate to his ſpouſe the things that appertaine to his poſſeſſion, for he that giueth unto her his body, and himſelfe wholly, how can it be, but that he muſt giue her all things elſe withall? and he that is poſſeſſed of the ſpouſe, how doth he not withall poſſeſſe alſo the things ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertayning to the ſpouſe? Here com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth loe to the view, a moſt ſwéet ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle, not onely of communion, but of a comfortable battell of victory of ſaluation and redemption.</p>
            <p>For in as much as Chriſt is God and Man, and ſuch a perſon, as neuer yet ſinned, neuer dyeth, nor is damned, yea ſuch a one, as neither can ſinne, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dye, nor be damned, and that his iuſtice
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:9429:28"/>
his life, his ſauing health, is vnvanquiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, euerlaſting and omnipotent, when as (I ſay) ſuch a perſon doth communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate to himſelfe, yea rather doth wedde (as his owne) the ſinne, death, and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of his ſpouſe through the wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did Kyng and vnion of Fayth. And that the caſe now ſtandeth none otherwiſe, then as if they were his owne proper pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar, euen as it himſelfe had ſinned, were trauelling, dying, and deſcending into hell, to bring all things in ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: And that ſinne, death, and hell could not ſwallow him, being all of neceſſity cleane ſwallowed vp in him by a miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous conflict (for his righteouſnes is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than the ſinnes of all men: his life ſurmounteth in power all death, his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing health is more victorious than all hell) euen ſo the faithfull ſoule, through the aſſuredneſſe of her faith in Chriſt her huſband, is deliuered from all ſinnes, made ſafe from death, garded from hell, and endowed with the euerlaſting righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, life, &amp; ſauing health of her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band Chriſt. On this wiſe Chriſt doth co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:9429:29"/>
her vnto himſelfe a glorious Spouſe without ſpotte and wrinckle, clenſing her with the fountaine in the word of life, that is to ſay, through faith, the word of life, of righteouſneſſe, and of ſaluation. Euen ſo doth he marry her vnto himſelfe in faith in mercy, and compaſſions, in iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and iudgement, as he teſtifieth in the ſecond of Oſée.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Oſe</hi> 2. The Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie of this royall marriage.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore who is able to value the roialtie of this mariage accordingly? who is able to comprehend the glorious riches of this grace? where this rich and louing husband Chriſt doth take vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to wife this poore and wicked Harlot, redéeming her from all euils, and gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing her with all his owne Iewels. For it is impoſſible now, that her owne ſinnes ſhould deſtroy her, ſithens they are laid vpon Chriſts ſhoulders, and ſwallowed vp in him, ſithens alſo it doth now poſſeſſe the ſame righteouſneſſe in her husband Chriſt, of the which ſhe may now embolden her ſelfe, and preſume vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them as in her owne right againſt all her owne ſinnes, againſt death and hell,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:9429:29"/>
and may with confidence encounter the enemy, and ſay, if I haue ſinned, yet my ſwéet husband Chriſt, in whom I doe beléeue, hath not ſinned, all whoſe riches are mine, and all mine are his: As in the Canticle of Salomon. <hi>My welbeloued husband to mee, and I vnto him</hi> This is that Paul ſpeaketh of in the firſt to the Corinths the fiftéenth Chapter.<note place="margin">Cor. <hi>1.</hi> the <hi>15.</hi> chapter.</note> 
               <hi>Than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked be God which hath giuen vs victory through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord: Euen the victory ouer ſin &amp; death.</hi> And in the ſame place he bringeth in, that <hi>ſinne is the ſting of Death, but the force of ſin is the law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hereof therefore you doe vnderſtand againe,<note place="margin">For what cauſe faith is ſo much eſteemed.</note> what the cauſe is that faith is ſo highly commended: that it is able alone to fulfill the law, &amp; to iuſtifie without any helpe of workes: For thou doſt perceiue how the firſt commandement,<note place="margin">The true worſhip of God.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt worſhip one God only,</hi> is now accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by Faith only: For if thou were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſole of the foot, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crown of the head but good workes, yet ſhouldſt thou not be iuſt, nor ſhouldeſt thou wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God, nor fulfill the firſt commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:9429:30"/>
for as much as God cannot be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped, vnleſſe the praiſe and glory of all truth and all goodneſſe be truly aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed vnto him: but this cannot works bring to paſſe, only the faith of the heart muſt atchieue this. For wee doe glorify and confeſſe him to be true, not by wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, but by beléeuing. In this reſpect Faith only is the righteouſneſſe of a Chriſtian man, and the accompliſhment of all the Commandents: For hee that doth accompliſh the firſt Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, doth fulfill all the reſt with no labour at all. For works being things without ſenſe, cannot glorify God, though they may be practiſed to Gods glory, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ioyned with faith. But wee, at this preſent, enquire not the works wrought, of what quality they be: but we doe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of the perſon that maketh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> works, that glorifieth and bringeth foorth the works:<note place="margin">Faith ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eeth works</note> And the ſame is the very Fayth of the heart, the head and ſubſtance of all our righteouſneſſe: whereupon it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that the doctrine that teacheth the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of the law by meanes of works,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:9429:30"/>
is blinde and perilous, for as much as before all works, it behooueth that all the Commandements bee accompliſhed, and that works doe follow after this fulfilling of the law, as wee ſhall heare more at large afterwards.</p>
            <p>But to the end wee may more mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly behold this grace which this our inward man doth poſſeſſe in Chriſt, it is to be obſerued, that in the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue of the firſt birth.</note> God did ſanctify to himſelfe the firſt borne of euery mankinde, &amp; the firſt brith was wonderfully eſtéemed, ſurmounting all other in double honour: Namely, in the Prieſthood, and in the kingdome, for the firſt begotten brother was Prieſt &amp; Lord of all other: vnder which ſhadow Chriſt was prefigured vnto vs, the true and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly firſt begotten of God the Father, &amp; of the virgin Mary, and the true King and Prieſt:<note place="margin">Whereof the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt.</note> but not according to the fleſh and the world, for his kingdome is not of this world, he raigneth and ſanctifieth in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall and heauenly things which are righteouſnes, truth, wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, peace, ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c. Not as though all things of this world
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:9429:31"/>
and of hell, were not alſo in ſubiection vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him (otherwiſe how could he preſerue and defend vs from them all) but becauſe his kingdome doth conſiſt neither in them nor of them. Euen ſo neither his Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood doth conſiſt in outward pompe of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell and geſtures (ſuch as the humane Prieſthood of Aaron was,<note place="margin">Chriſts Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood.</note> and as our ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Prieſthood is at this day) but in ſpirituall things, by the which he doth make interceſſion for vs vnto God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in heauen, by a certaine inuiſible of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and there doth offer vp himſelfe, and performeth all things that behooued a Prieſt to doe.<note place="margin">Prieſtly office. Paul to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brues.</note> Euen as Paul doth deſcribe him by a figure of <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> in his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the Hebrues. Neither doth he on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pray, and make interceſſion for vs, but alſo doth teach &amp; inſtruct vs, inwardly in ſpirit with the liuely doctrine of his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which two are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peculiar properties of a Prieſt, which alſo is figured in carnall Prieſts by praiers &amp; viſible preachings.<note place="margin">How it is to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken that faithfull Chriſtians be Prieſts.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And euen as Chriſt by his firſt birth did obtaine theſe two dignities, ſo doth he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part and communicate the ſame to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:9429:31"/>
his faithfull ſpouſe, by the right of the foreſaid mariage, wherby they are al ſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, whoſoeuer are eſpouſed to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> huſband. And hereof commeth it, that we all that beléeue in Chriſt are Prieſts and kings in Chriſt, as in the firſt of Peter the ſecond Chapter, <hi>You be a choſen kindred,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of adoption, a kingly prieſthood, and a prieſtly kingdome, to the end you ſhould ſhew forth his power, who hath caled you from darkneſſe, into his maruellous light:</hi> which two are thus to be taken.</p>
            <p>Firſt as concerning the kingdome,<note place="margin">Chriſtian kings.</note> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery faithfull Chriſtian through Fayth is ſo aduanced aboue all other things, that in ſpirituall power he is become Lord o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all, ſo that none of all the creatures can doe him any harme at all: Nay rather all things are made ſubiect vnto him, and compelled to ſerue for his ſafety, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the teſtimony of <hi>Paul</hi> in the eight to the Romans.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.</note> 
               <hi>All things doe worke together to the elect to good.</hi> Likewiſe in the firſt to the Corinthians, the third Chapter. <hi>All things are yours,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>whether it be life or death, things preſent, or things
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:9429:32"/>
to come,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Note.</note> 
               <hi>but you are Chriſts.</hi> Not that to euery Chriſtian, all préeminence is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in bodily power to poſſeſſe and rule o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all things (which furious frenſie hath bewitched many our Prelates euery where) for this dominion is proper to Kings, Princes, and Potentates of the earth: whereas the very vſe and manner of our liues, doth ſufficently teach vs, that we are ſubiect to all, that we doe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure many tribulations, yea, &amp; euen die y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death. Nay, rather, by how much a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian doth excell in Chriſtianity, by ſo much the more is he ſubiect vnto all incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences, vexations, and deaths, as wee may eaſily ſée in the very flower of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt borne Chriſt himſelfe and all his holy bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.<note place="margin">The ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</note> This power is ſpirituall, which doth beare dominion euen in the middeſt of enemies, and is mighty euen amiddeſt the very tortures, which is nothing elſe in effect, but that power is made perfect in weakneſſe, and that in all things I may make gaine for my ſafety: inſomuch, that the croſſe and death it ſelfe may bee compelled to ſerue for my behoofe, and to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:9429:32"/>
worke my ſaluation: and this is that high and notable dignity, yea, that true &amp; om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent power, the ſpirituall kingdome, wherein nothing is ſo good, nothing ſo bad, which ſhall not worke to my good, ſo that I beléeue. And yet haue I néed of nothing (ſithens only faith doth ſuffice to ſaluation) but that faith may in the ſame exerciſe her force, &amp; the dominion of her li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. Behold now this is that ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble power and liberty of Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>So alſo we be not only moſt frée kings of all other, but we be Prieſts alſo for euer,<note place="margin">We be Prieſts for euer.</note> which doth farre ſurpaſſe all kingdomes: For through our Prieſthood we are made worthy to appeare before God, to plead and pray for other men, &amp; one to inſtruct the other the things that are of God. For theſe be the offices peculiar vnto Prieſts, which can in no wiſe be committed to any vnbeléeuer. Such a prerogatiue hath Chriſt obtained for vs, that as ioynt bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, coheires, and ioyntkings, ſo alſo we ſhould be vnto him ioyntprieſts, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming boldly with confidence through the ſpirit of Faith to preach vnto the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:9429:33"/>
of God, and to cry vnto him <hi>Abba</hi> Father, and to pray for each other, and to doe all things y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſee to be executed &amp; fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured by the viſible and corporall function of the Prieſts But vnto the vnbeléeuer nothing ſerueth or worketh vnto good,<note place="margin">All things euill to the vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuer.</note> but hee is become ſeruant of all other, to whom all things turne vnto euill, becauſe he doth wickedly employ all his endeauor for his owne behoofe, and not to the glory of God. And by this meanes he is neither Prieſt but prophane, whoſe prayer tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vnto ſinne, nor doth appeare before God, becauſe God doth not heare ſinners. Wherfore who is able to comprehend the preheminence of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dignity? which through her own kingly power executeth dominion ouer all things, ouer death, life, ſinne, &amp;c. and which through her prieſtly glory is able to work all things in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſight of God, becauſe God doth bring to paſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> things for the which he doth pray &amp; wiſh, as it is written, <hi>He ſhall worke the will of them that feare him, &amp; ſhall heare their petitions, &amp; ſhall ſaue them,</hi> To this glory ſurely is no poſſible acceſſe by working,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:9429:33"/>
but onely by faith and beliefe.</p>
            <p>By the premiſſes may euery man ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily perceiue,<note place="margin">The liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</note> by what meanes a Chriſtian man is frée from all, and Lord ouer all: ſo that to become iuſt and ſaued, he ſhall not néed any works at all, but through faith only obtaineth all thoſe things ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently: who if he would be ſo mad, as to preſume to be made a iuſt, a frée, and a ſafe Chriſtian, by force of any good work, he ſhould ſurely loſe his faith forthwith, together with all his good works, which folly is aptly moralized in that fable of Eſop, where the Dogge ſwimmeth in the water, &amp; carrying fleſh in his mouth, deluded with the ſhadow of the ſame fleſh glittering in the water, whiles gaping with open mouth, he ſnatcheth after the ſhadow, he both loſeth the true fleſh, and the ſhadow withall.</p>
            <p>Héere you will aſke of me, If all be Prieſts that bee in Chriſts Church: by what title then may they (whom wee call commonly Prieſts now) bee diſcerned from Lay men? I doe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere: There is a great iniury com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:9429:34"/>
againſt theſe words, to witte, Prieſt, Clarke, Spirituall, Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall, whiles they be tranſlated from all the reſt of the Chriſtians, and be abrid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to theſe few, which through euill cuſtome are tearmed Church men: For holy ſcripture doth make no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them, ſauing that it entituleth them by the names of Miniſters, Seruants, and Stewards, which doe now vaunt themſelues to be Popes, Biſhoppes, and Lords, which ought to miniſter to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in preaching the word, to teach the faith of Chriſt and Chriſtian liberty: For albeit this be true, that wée be all Prieſts indifferently, yet can wée not all, nor yet ought we all miniſter &amp; teach pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely, though we were all able to doe ſo: For ſo doth Paul teach in his firſt to the Corinths, the fourth Chapter. <hi>Let men ſo eſteeme of vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor. c.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>as miniſters of Chriſt, and Stewards of the myſteries of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">To what iſſue the miniſtry Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall is come.</note>But this Stewardſhip is now enhaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced vnto ſo mighty a Potentate &amp; pompe of power, and vnto a certaine terrible ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranne, that no kingdomes of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:9429:34"/>
ne yet any Empyres of the whole world are not able to counteruaile the ſame in ſtatelineſſe. As though lay people were a certaine ſomewhat beſides and no Chriſtians at all. Through which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſeneſſe it is come to paſſe, that the true knowledge of Chriſtian grace, Chriſtian faith, and Chriſtian liberty, yea of Chriſt himſelfe, is come wholly to vtter ruine, whiles, in the meane ſpace, an importable clogge and intolerable bondage of mens workes and traditions are crawled vp in his place, and we (according to Ieremies lamentations) are become vaſſalles of the moſt vileſt varlettes of the world, which doe abuſe our miſery to worke all infamous filthineſſe, and ſhamefull reproaches of their beaſtly licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>But to returne to our purpoſe againe.<note place="margin">How Chriſt ought to be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched.</note> I ſuppoſe that by the foreſaid demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions it is made manifeſt, that it ſufficeth not to a true Chriſtian man to preach the workes, life, and doctrine of Chriſt, after an hiſtoricall manner, and vtter the ſame, as in telling of tales, as though
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:9429:35"/>
to know them to bee patternes of fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming our liues, were enough (like as they vſe to preach which are now ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted the beſt) much leſſe if it bee vtterly concealed, and inſtéede thereof mens conſtitutions and traditions bee taught to ſupply the place. There bée ſome now a dayes, and they not a few, which to this purpoſe doe preach and teach Chriſt, that they may mooue the affections of the people to bewaile the paſſion and torments which Chriſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, and to bee diſpleaſant againſt the Iewes, and ſuch other childiſh and fond matters of no great importance. But Chriſt ought to be preached to this end, that faith in him may encreaſe, that it may appeare, that it is not enough, that there is a Chriſt, but that hee may bee a Chriſt (which is a Sauiour) vnto thee and vnto me: And that he doth work the ſame in vs, which is me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned of him, &amp; is agréeable to the name whereby hee is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: which faith ſpringeth, floriſheth, and is preſerued by this, if the preaching doe notifie the cauſe wherefore Chriſt
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:9429:35"/>
came, what he brought with him, what he gaue, and to what vſe and purpoſe hee is to be embraced. And this commeth to paſſe, where Chriſtian liberty (which we doe attaine by him) is truly taught: and by what meanes all wee Chriſtians are Kings and Prieſts: wherein alſo wee be Lords ouer all: and vpon what this our affiance (that whatſoeuer wee doe is well pleaſing and acceptable to GOD) is grounded, as I haue ſaid before.</p>
            <p>For whoſe heart hearing theſe things will not melt for very ioy,<note place="margin">The fruit of true preaching</note> and waxe raui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in loue of Chriſt, hauing receiued ſo great a conſolation? to the which loue hee can neuer poſſibly attaine by any lawes or workes at all: what is hee that can hurt ſuch a heart, or may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall the ſame with feare? If conſcience of ſinne doe ruſh vpon him, or horror of death amaze him, loe, it is ready to truſt in the Lord, nor is afraid for any ſuch e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill noiſe, nor is diſquieted, vntill it do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe the enemies, for it beléeueth that Chriſts righteouſneſſe is become his
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:9429:36"/>
owne righteouſneſſe, and that his ſinne is now no longer his owne, but Chriſts ſinne. But it behoueth that all ſinne bée ſwallowed vp at the very ſight of Chriſt, through the faith of Chriſt, as hath béene declared before, and learne now with the Apoſtle, to treade vpon, and triumph ouer ſinne and death, and to ſay, <hi>Death, where is thy ſting? Death, where is thy vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie? the ſting of Death is ſinne, but the power of ſinne is the Law. God be than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, who hath giuen vs victory through Ieſus our Lord,</hi> for death is ſwallowed vp through the conqueſt, not of Chriſt onely, but our owne alſo, becauſe it commeth to paſſe by our Faith, that the conqueſt is made ours, and that in the ſame wee doe ouercome.</p>
            <p>Let this ſuffice touching the inward man, touching his freedome, &amp; touching the principall righteouſneſſe of Faith, which neither neede th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>awes nor workes, which will turne to his deſtruction that dare preſume to be iuſtified by them. Now let vs returne to the other part, to witte, the outward man: For in this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:9429:36"/>
anſwere ſhall be made to all them,<note place="margin">The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of them which doe not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yea rather which doe not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue what faith is.</note> who being offended with the word of Faith, and with the things that haue béene ſpoken of before, doe reply on this wiſe againſt vs. If Faith doe accompliſh all things, and if Faith bée onely and alone ſufficient vnto righteouſneſſe, to what end then are wée commanded to doe good déedes? we may goe play vs then, and worke no working at all, being furniſhed ſufficiently with faith, I doe anſwere, <hi>Not ſo yee vngodly, not ſo.</hi> In déede this matter would euen ſo fare, as you ſay, if we were perfectly and altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the inward and ſpirituall men: which wée cannot bée in any wiſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the laſt day at the riſing again of the dead. So long as wée be clothed with this mortall fleſh, wée doe but beginne and procéede outward in our courſe towards perfection, which will bée conſummated in the life to come. And for this cauſe, the Apoſtle in the eight to the Romanes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.</note> doth call this the firſt fruits of the Spirit, which we doe enioy in this life, the tenth and fulneſſe of which
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:9429:37"/>
ſpirit we ſhall receiue in the life to come. To this belongeth that whereof we ſpak before, namely, that a Chriſtian man is ſeruant of all, and ſubiect to all, for in this that hee is frée, hee worketh nothing, but in this, that he is a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, hee worketh all things. Now let vs ſée how theſe two will ſtand together. Albeit man bee ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently iuſtified by faith in the inward Man Spiritually, as I ſayd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, enioying all that hee ought to haue, ſauing that hee muſt by dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly encreaſings enlarge this ſame faith, and riches of grace, vntill he be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clothed of his fleſh, yet remayneth ſtill in this mortall life, vpon the face of the earth, wherein he muſt of very neceſſity nouriſh his owne body,<note place="margin">From whence works take their beginning</note> and be conuerſant amongſt men. And euen here now works doe begin to take their entrance. Héere we may not giue our ſelues to idleneſſe. Here now we muſt apply our ſelues ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly to exerciſe this body with faſtings, watchings, labours, and other moderate diſciplines, to bring it in ſubiection to the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:9429:37"/>
ſpirit, that it may become obedient to faith, and conforme it ſelfe to the inward man, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it rebell not, nor hinder the ſpirit, following therein his owne naturall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, if it be not otherwiſe tamed: for the inward man being alike faſhioned vnto God, and created after the image of God, through faith, is both ioyfull, and comfortable, for the loue he hath to Chriſt,<note place="margin">The only worke of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man.</note> in whom he is endued with ſo many good things, whereupon in this only doth it occupy it ſelfe, namely, to ſerue the Lord with a frée loue, with ioy, and thanks.</p>
            <p>Now whiles it is exerciſed in this courſe, behold in her owne fleſh it findeth a contrary will, which trauelleth altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſerue the world, and to ſéeke the things that are her owne, which the ſpirit of Faith cannot away withall, nor is able to endure it, and therefore with valiant courage attempteth to ſubdue and tame this rebellious will, as Paul witneſſeth in the ſeuenth to the Romans, <hi>I am deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Law of God in mine inward man, but I ſee another Law in my mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, rebelling againſt the Law of my
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:9429:38"/>
minde, &amp; leading me captiue into the law of ſinne.</hi> And in another place, <hi>I do cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſe my body, &amp; bring it into ſubiection, leſt whiles I preach to others, I my ſelfe may be found a caſtaway.</hi> And in the fifth to the Galath.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Galath.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>They that are of Chriſt haue crucified the fleſh, and the concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcences thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of what minde wee ought to be in doing good works.</note>But neither we may do theſe workes in any wiſe, being of the opinion that man may bee iuſtified through them in the ſight of God. For this falſe opinion is not tolerable in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eye of Faith, which Faith is the only righteouſneſſe before God. But in theſe workes wee muſt bee of the minde, ſo to bring the fleſh into ſubiection, and to cleanſe the euill concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcences thereof, that it may not bend the view of the eye to any thing elſe, than to the mortifying of euill concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence and luſt: For when the ſoule is waſhed cleane through faith, and made the dearling of Chriſt, it would alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that all things elſe, yea, and her owne body chiefely might be purged together withall, to the end all things in her
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:9429:38"/>
might loue, and glorifie God together, whereby it commeth to paſſe, that man through an enforcing neceſſity of the fleſh, may not giue himſelfe to idleneſſe, &amp; for that cauſe is conſtrayned to doe many good things, to the end hee may bring his body into ſubiection. And yet theſe works are not of ſuch power, as to bee able to worke mans iuſtification before God. But man of a very pure loue, doth worke the ſame, to the ſeruice and obedience of God, beholding in them nothing elſe than Gods good will, vnto the which he would moſt willingly and dutifully yéeld alhum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bie obedience in all things.</p>
            <p>By this meanes euery man may eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly direct himſelfe,<note place="margin">How the body ought to be cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſed. Note.</note> how he ought moſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly (as the ſaying is) and moſt commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſly attemper his owne body, for hée ſhall faſt ſo much, watch and labour to much, as ſhall ſeeme moſt expedient, for the taming of the wantonneſſe and licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſneſſe of his body. But thoſe that doe vaunt to be iuſtified by works, doe regard not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mortificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh, and the luſts thereof, but the works the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, being of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:9429:39"/>
opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that if they do very many, &amp; great good déeds, they are thereby in good caſe, &amp; are become iuſt therewith: ſomtime hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the braines, and deſtroying nature vtterly, or at leaſt making it vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table. And this is a wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derful folly, &amp; groſſe ignorance of Chriſtian life, and of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian faith, to haue a will to bee iuſtified and ſaued by works without faith.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A notable ſimilitude.</note>But to the end that which we haue ſaid may more eaſily be conceiued, let vs make demonſtration therof by ſimilitudes. The works of a Chriſtian man being iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſaued through his owne faith, by the mere and frée mercy of God, ought to bee of none other value and eſtimation, than the workes of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue,</hi> and all their children ſhould haue bin in Paradiſe if they had neuer ſinned, of whom God ſpake in the ſecond of Geneſis on this wiſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>God did place man, whom he crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, into Paradiſe, that hee might worke and manure the ſame.</hi> But God created Adam iuſt and perfect, and without ſinne, ſo that he ſhould not haue néed to bee iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified and made perfect by any his owne
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:9429:39"/>
worke, endeauour, and ſafe kéeping. But to the end he ſhould not be idle, God en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned him this worke, to manure Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, and to kéepe it, which works had bin truly moſt frée, wrought in reſpect of nothing, but of Gods good pleaſure only, and not to procure righteouſnes thereby, wherewith he was fully endued already, and which alſo ſhould haue bin ioyntly in the creation of vs all.</p>
            <p>To the ſame effect bee the workes of the faithfull beléeuer,<note place="margin">Faith doth reſtore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe.</note> who through his owne faith being reſtored againe into Paradiſe, and created againe of new, née<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth no workes to become, or made iuſt thereby. But becauſe he ſhould not bee idle, but manure his owne body, and kéepe it, he muſt doe ſuch works of fréedome in reſpect of Gods good will onely, ſauing that is not yet fully created againe anew with perfect faith and loue, which behoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to be encreaſed daily, yet not by force of workes, but of their owne ſtrength. Take yet another example.<note place="margin">Another examples</note> An holy Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop conſecrating a Church, Biſhopping children, or executing ſome other parcell
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:9429:40"/>
of his function, is not himſelfe conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a Biſhop by force of thoſe exerciſes, nay rather vnleſſe he had bin a conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Biſhop before, none of al theſe works could haue béene to any purpoſe, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted rather childiſh, altogether fooliſh and apiſh. Euen ſo a Chriſtian man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing firſt conſecrated by his owne faith, doth worke good works indéed, yet is hée made thereby neuer a deale the more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or the more a Chriſtian, for this is the work of faith only, yea rather, vnleſſe hée did firſt beléeue, and were a Chriſtian be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, all his works would not be worth a ſtraw, but rather very wicked, and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſinnes.</p>
            <p>And for this cauſe theſe two ſayings bée true,<note place="margin">Two no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</note> namely, Good workes doe not make a good man, but a good man doth make the workes to bee good. And euill workes doe not make an euill man, but an euill man doth make the workes to be euill, ſo that it behooueth alwayes, that the ſubſtance or perſon bee good firſt, before all good works, and that good works follow then by order, and procéed from a
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:9429:40"/>
good perſon, as Chriſt himſelfe witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth. <hi>An euill tree doth not bring good fruit, and a good tree doth not bring euill fruit.</hi> For it is euidently knowne by experience, that the fruit doth not beare the trée, and that the trée doth not grow in the fruit, but contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, the trées doe beare the fruits, and the fruit doth grow in the trées. Therefore, as it is neceſſary that the trée bee firſt before the fruit, and that the fruit doth not make the trées good or euill: But contrarily, ſuch as the trée is, ſuch is the fruit, ſo is it neceſſary, that the perſon, or man himſelfe be either good or badde firſt, before hee make a good or bad worke, and that his workes make him neither good nor badde, but the man himſelfe maketh his owne workes good or badde.</p>
            <p>Semblable héereunto may wée ſée in all occupations.<note place="margin">Another example.</note> An euill houſe or a good houſe doth not make an euill or a good Carpenter, but a good or bad Carpenter maketh a good or badde houſe. And ſo ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally in all kindes of manuall occupati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:9429:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and ſciences, no péece of worke doth make the Artificer good or bad, but ſuch as the Artificer is, ſuch worke maketh he: euen ſo fareth it in the caſe of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s works. Such as the perſon is either in faith or in vnbeléefe, ſuch is his work, if either done in faith, and ſo good, or done in vnbeléefe, &amp; ſo euill. But contrariwiſe, it is not ſo, to wit, ſuch as the worke is, ſuch is the perſon, made in faith or vnbeléefe, for as workes doe not make a man to be a belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, ſo neither doe they make a man righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous.<note place="margin">Only faith iuſtifieth.</note> But faith, as it maketh man belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and righteous, ſo doth it make his works to be good. For as much therefore as works doe not iuſtifie any man, and that it behooueth man to be righteous be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he worke any good worke: it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth moſt manifeſtly, that faith onely by the mere mercy of God through Chriſt Ieſu in his word, doth make worthy, and ſufficiently iuſtifie, and ſaue the perſon: and that a Chriſtian man néedeth no worke nor law at all, thereby to attaine ſaluation, for that through faith hee is frée from all law, and doth fréely worke all
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:9429:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
things that he worketh of his owne mere good will, reſpecting therein neither pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, nor ſaluation, but only the good will of God, for as much as he is now alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy fully repleniſhed, and made ſafe by the grace of God through his owne faith.</p>
            <p>Euen ſo no good worke auaileth to righteouſneſſe and ſaluation to the vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeuing perſon. On the other ſide,<note place="margin">The vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing perſon is not made euill by works.</note> no euill worke maketh him euill or damnable, but his owne vnbeléefe, which both maketh the trée euill, and withall, maketh the workes euill and damnable, whereupon in this, that any perſon is made good or badde, he doth not receiue this being good or badde by works, but this his good or euill taketh beginning from the roote of faith or vnbeleefe, as the wiſe man recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, <hi>The beginning of ſin is to fall from God,</hi> which is in effect, to be vnbeléeuing.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.</note> And Paul in the 11 to the Hebrewes, <hi>It behooueth him that commeth to God, to beleeue.</hi> The ſame alſo ſpeaketh Chriſt, <hi>Either make the tree good, and the fruit thereof good, or make the tree euill, and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:9429:42"/>
the fruit thereof euill,</hi> as if he might ſay, who ſo will make good fruits, muſt begin at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trée firſt, &amp; plant vpon a good ſtock, ſo who ſo will make good works, muſt begin, not at the working, but at the beléeuing, which beléefe doth make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſon good, for nothing maketh the perſon good, but faith, nor any thing maketh him euill, but vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léefe.<note place="margin">Works do make a man good, but that is in the ſight of men. <hi>Matth</hi> 7.</note> Indéed this is true, that by works man is made good or euill in the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of men, but this is as much in effect, as to doe it to vnderſtand, and let it be knowne who bee good, or who bee euill, whereof Chriſt ſpeaketh in the ſeuenth of Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew, <hi>You ſhall know them by their fruits.</hi> But this knowledge conſiſteth only in ſhew, and outward appearance, &amp; ſemblance, wherein many are deceiued that preſume to teach and preſcribe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by men may bee iuſtified in the meane time, making not once ſo much mention of Faith at all, masking ſtill in their own miſmaze,<note place="margin">The origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of ſome mens er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour.</note> alwayes deceiued, and deceiuing others, going forward from worſe vnto worſe, blind guides of the blind, wearying themſelues with a multitude of works, &amp;
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:9429:42"/>
yet neuer attaining to true righteouſnes, of whom Paul writeth in the 1.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.</note> to Tim. the 3. Chap. <hi>Hauing indeed an vtter ſhew of holines, but denying the power there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, alwayes learning, but neuer attaining to the knowledge of the truth.</hi> Therefore behooueth him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> will not wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der out of the way, with theſe blind guides, to enter into a déeper co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vtter ſhew of workes, of lawes, &amp; doctrines of workes, but muſt rather with a quite contrary aſpect pry into the perſon, and note di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently the reaſon, whereby man is iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied: and here ſhall he finde, that man is iuſtified and ſaued, not by workes, nor by the law, but by the word of God, that is to ſay, by the promiſe of his grace, and by faith, that ſo the glory thereof may redound to the maieſty of God, <hi>Who hath ſaued vs that beleeue, not by the works of righteouſneſſe which wee haue done, but according to his owne mercy, through the word of his owne grace.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rules to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the doctrines of many.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Wherby it remaineth eaſie to be knowne in what reſpect good works are to be reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted or embraced, &amp; in what ſenſe all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:9429:43"/>
of men touching workes ought to be vnderſtood: for if workes be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to righteouſneſſe, and be practiſed by a peruerſe Leuiathan, and of that falſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, to preſume vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> obtaining true iuſtification therby, they do now enforce a neceſſity vnauoidable, &amp; do vtterly extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh liberty &amp; faith withall, and ſo euen by this meanes are now no more good, but méerely damnable, for they be not now frée, but blaſphemous to the grace of God, whoſe onely property is through faith to iuſtifie and ſaue, which things workes doe affect to bring to paſſe, not of any their ability, but by a wicked foolehar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe only, iſſuing from our own groſſe ignorance: by reaſon whereof they doe violently ruſhe, and intrude into the office of grace and the glory thereof.<note place="margin">The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Luthers Doctrine.</note> For this cauſe therefore wée doe not reiect good workes, but rather doe moſt hartely em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace and teach them: Neither doe wée condemne them in reſpect of themſelues, but in reſpect of the wicked addition gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto them, and peruerſe opinion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued of them, in thattayning of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe:
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:9429:43"/>
whereby it commeth to paſſe, that they appeare good onely in ſhew, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not good in déede, and in truth, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by being themſelues deceiued, and decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing others alſo, as rauening wolues clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in ſhéepes skinnes.</p>
            <p>And this Leuiathan and peruerſe opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in workes cannot poſſibly be reclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, where pure faith wanteth,<note place="margin">The work of Leuia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than.</note> nor is remoueable from theſe holy workemen before that Faith the vanquiſher thereof come in place and beare dominion in the heart. Nature is not of it ſelfe forcible enough to expell it, no not ſo much as to take notice therof, but eſtéemeth it in place of a moſt holy will: wheras if cuſtome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, &amp; take déep rooting in this peruerſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of nature (as is already brought to paſſe through wicked teachers) it is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable diſeaſe, and leadeth aſtray innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable people into deſtruction vnrecoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. And therfore albeit it be a commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable thing to preach &amp; write gloriouſly of repentance, confeſſion, and ſatiſfaction, yet if they ſurceaſe here, and procéede no further, euen to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inſtructing of faith: ſuch
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:9429:44"/>
doctrine doubtleſſe is deceiueable and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiliſh: For euen ſo Chriſt with his belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Iohn did not only ſay, <hi>Repent yee of your ſinnes:</hi> But added alſo the word of faith, <hi>For, the kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is at hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Preachers muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort to Faith.</note>For the one part of Gods word ought not to be preached alone but both together muſt be taught: both new and old muſt be deliuered out of this treaſury, aſwel the voyce of the Law, as the word of Grace. The voyce of the Law muſt be vttered, that the people may be terrified, and fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to know their ſinnes, and thereby be turned to repentance, and amendment of their former life. But here forthwith muſt not ſtay be made: for this were only to wound, and not miniſter playſter: to lance, and not to heale: to kill, and not to quicken: to lead vnto hell gates, and not to deliuer from thence: to throw downe alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and not raiſe vp. Wherefore the word of grace alſo, &amp; the word of promiſed forgiuenes, ought likewiſe to be preached, to inſtruct &amp; raiſe vp the faith, without the which in vaine is the doctrine of the law, of contrition, of repentance, &amp; of all other
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:9429:44"/>
things alſo practiſed and preached.</p>
            <p>Indéed there remaine as yet certaine preachers of Repentance and Grace,<note place="margin">From whence repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance or Faith doe proceed.</note> but they doe not diſcloſe the law, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God, in that liuely ſpirit &amp; force as others capacities may attaine to the true fountaines and ſpring head of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Grace. For Repentance pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céedeth from out the law of God, but faith or Grace doth iſſue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gods promiſe. As the Apoſtle witneſſeth in the tenth to the Romans. <hi>Faith commeth by hearing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>but hearing commeth of the word of Chriſt:</hi> Wherefore it commeth to paſſe, that man receiueth conſolation, and is rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp through Faith of Gods promiſes, who otherwiſe through the threatnings and terrours of Gods Law, is brought low, and throwne downe into the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of himſelfe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 29.</note> Whereof the Pſalmiſt in the xxix. Pſalme. <hi>Mourning ſhall dwell vntill the euening, and ioyfulneſſe vntill the morning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let this ſuffice to haue béene ſpoken of works in generall,<note place="margin">Of works towards our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</note> and of thoſe works alſo which a Chriſtian man doth exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:9429:45"/>
towards his owne body. Laſtly, wee will ſpeak of thoſe workes which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian doth employ to the vſe of his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. For man doth not liue vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe only in this mortall body, to worke in the ſame, but to all men generally vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth, Nay rather man liueth only to other men, and not to himſelfe: For to this end doth hee keepe his body in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection, that he may thereby more ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and fréely ſerue to the neceſſities of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. As witneſſeth Paul in the <hi>14.</hi> to the Romans.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>No man liueth to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and no man dyeth to himſelfe. For he that liueth, liueth vnto God, and hee that dyeth, dyeth vnto God.</hi> It is not poſſible therefore, that in this life man ſhould be idle and vnfruitfull towards his neighbours. For of very neceſſity he muſt talke, worke, and bee conuerſant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt man. <hi>Euen as Chriſt made to our likeneſſe in properties,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Baruch.</hi> 3. A Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an muſt apply him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to all men.</note> 
               <hi>was found to bee as man, and conuerſant amongſt men.</hi> as Baruch teſtifieth in his third Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>And yet he néedeth none of all theſe to
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:9429:45"/>
procure righteouſneſſe and ſaluation. And therefore in all his works behooueth him to be ſo framed in minde, and to direct his whole affection only to miniſter to the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of others, to ſéeke the commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of others, in all his déeds, hauing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to nothing elſe, than to the behoofe and profit of his neighbour. For euen ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle commandeth vs to worke with our hands, that we may haue wherewith to reléeue the neceſſity of our brethren: whereas otherwiſe he might haue ſaid,<note place="margin">To what end the body muſt be che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed.</note> to haue wherwith to cheriſh our own bodies: but let him giue (ſaith he) to him that is in néed: For the property of true Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is, to regard the ſtate of his owne bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, to this end, that through health &amp; well preſeruing the ſame, he may be able to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to gaine riches, and to employ them to the reléefe of the néedy. That ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g member may helpe the weake member, and that we may be the ſonnes of God, carefull, and trauelling each for other, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring one anothers burthen, and by this meanes fulfilling the law of Chriſt. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold here the true Chriſtian life, this is
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:9429:46"/>
the natural liuely faith,<note place="margin">The true Chriſtian faith.</note> effectuall through loue: that is to ſay, when it breaketh forth into the worke of moſt frée ſeruice, with ioy &amp; loue, wherin he doth fréely and of his owne accord, miniſter to others, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging it ſelf fully ſatiſfied with the abundance and riches of his own faith.</p>
            <p>After the ſame maner when Paul had made euident to the Philippians, how rich they were made through the faith of Chriſt, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which they had receiued plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of all things, he giueth vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another leſſon, and ſaith, <hi>If you haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued any conſolation of Chriſt, if any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of loue, if any fellowſhip of the holy ghoſt, fulfil then my ioy, that ye may be al of one mind, &amp; be endued all with the like loue, being alike minded, &amp; thinking all one thing, eſteeming nothing of your ſelues through co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tention or vaine glory, but ſtriuing to excel ech other in humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, euery one regarding not the things of his own, but the neceſſities of others.</hi> Loe here by this rule of the Apoſtle, wée ſée plainely the life of true Chriſtians to conſiſt in this, that all their workes be
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:9429:46"/>
directed to the commoditie of others, for as much as euery perſon doth ſo much abound through his owne Faith, that all other workes, and all his whole life, doth ouerflowe vnto him, wherewith he may be able to miniſter vnto, and profit our neighbour, of a frée, and voluntary good will, and beneuolence.</p>
            <p>And to this effect hée exciteth vnto them Chriſt for an example, ſaying,<note place="margin">The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prauers of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</note> 
               <hi>Let the ſame minde be in you, which was in Chriſt Ieſu,</hi> who when hee was in the ſhape of God, thought it no robbery to be equall with God. <hi>Neuertheleſſe he made himſelfe of no reputation, taking vpon him the ſhape of a ſeruant, and became like vnto men, and was found in appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell as a man, he humbled himſelfe &amp; was made obedient euen vnto the death.</hi> For this moſt holeſome word of the Apoſtle haue they hidden in darkeneſſe from vs, which were altogether ignorant in the ſpéeches of the Apoſtle, namely, <hi>The ſhape of God, the ſhape of Seruant, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell and the likeneſſe of men,</hi> and did apply the ſame prepoſterouſly, to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:9429:47"/>
of diuinity, and humanity: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Pauls meaning was, that whereas Chriſt was fully beautified with the ſhape of God, and abundantly flowing with the ſtore of all good things, ſo that he néeded not any worke, nor any paſſion to make him righteous and ſaued (for hée did abſolutely poſſeſſe all thoſe things, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the firſt beginning of himſelfe) yet was he not puft vp in pride with theſe, nor was lift vp aboue vs, nor did chalenge to himſelfe a certaine power ouer vs, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit he might in his owne right haue clay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the ſame: But contrariwiſe, did ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue himſelfe in labour, in workes, in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, and in doing, that he might be like vnto other men, both in apparell &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, none otherwiſe, than as man, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as if he had néeded all theſe, and had poſſeſſed no parcell of the ſhape of God: all which neuertheleſſe he vndertooke for our ſakes, to the end he might miniſter vnto our neceſſities, and that all things might bée made ours, which hee ſhould bring to paſſe in this ſhape of a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:9429:47"/>Euen ſo a Chriſtian man being ful and abounding through his faith like vnto Chriſt his head,<note place="margin">A Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme himſelfe to Chriſt.</note> ought to be contented with this ſhape of God obtained through Faith (ſauing that he ought to increaſe the ſame Faith, as I ſaid before, vntill it be made perfect) for this is the life of man, his righteouſneſſe, and ſaluation, both ſauing the perſon, making him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable, and furniſhing him with all things whatſoeuer Chriſt doth poſſeſſe, as is before mentioned, which alſo Paul in the firſt to the Galathians doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, ſaying: <hi>But in this that I liue in the fleſh I liue in the faith of the ſonne of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And although he be on this wiſe frée fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all workes, yet in this freedome ought be neuertheleſſe to make himſelfe of no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, and put on the ſhape of a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, and to become like vnto men, to be found in apparell as a man, and to miniſter, and to helpe, and by al means poſſible to worke his neighbours com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity, euen after the ſelfe ſame manner as he feeleth, that God hath done, and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:9429:48"/>
daily doth for him through Chriſt, and this alſo he muſt doe <hi>Gratis</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all reſpect, ſauing in reſpect of Gods good pleaſure, and euen after this manner muſt hée thinke vnfained<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an man.</note>Behold my good God hath giuen vnto mee moſt vnworthy and damned caitife, beyond all deſert, of his méere and frée mercy, in Chriſt Ieſu, all the treaſures of righteouſneſſe and ſaluation, ſo that henceforth I ſhall not ſtand in want of any thing at all, but of Fayth, which may firmely beléeue in Chriſt: Wherefore to this ſo louing a father, who hath ouerwhelmed mée with theſe his ineſtimable riches, why ſhould not I frankely, ioyfully, with all my heart, and with all my moſt lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and willing ſoule, yeelde all ſeruice whatſoeuer I doe know to bee well pleaſing, and is acceptable in his eyes.</p>
            <p>Wherfore I will giue my ſelfe wholly a certain Chriſt vnto my neighbour, euen as Chriſt gaue himſelfe vnto me, and will
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:9429:48"/>
doe nothing in this tranſitory life, but that which I ſhall perceiue to be neceſſary, commodious, and profitable for my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, in as much, as I am ſufficiently enough enriched with all good things in Chriſt through Faith.</p>
            <p>Lo here out of Faith floweth Loue,<note place="margin">The fruit of Faith. Behold gentle Reader how wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily is Luther re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proched.</note> &amp; reioycing in the Lord, and out of Loue floweth likewiſe a chéerefull, liberall, and frée heart to miniſter to the neceſſity of thy neighbour, frankely of thy owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, ſo that here now is no conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on had of gratitude, or ingratitude, of praiſe or diſpraiſe, of vantage or of loſſe: For neither doth hee apply hereunto to winne the fauour of men, nor maketh any difference betwixt friends or foes, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecteth the thankefull or vnthankfull, but moſt frankely and with moſt gladſome cheare doth yéelde himſelfe wholy, and all that he poſſeſſeth, without regard whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he loſe the ſame in the vnthankfull, or employ it on the deſeruing: For euen ſo his father doth, diſpoſing all things to all abundantly and moſt freely, making his ſun to ſhine vpon the good and the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:9429:49"/>
In like manner, the ſonne doth work and ſuffer nothing but of a frée and chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ioy, wherewith through Chriſt hee is delighted in God the giuer of ſo great and ineſtimable treaſures.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">We ought to know how great things are giuen vs.</note>You ſée therefore, if wee acknowledge all thoſe things which are giuen vnto vs, of greateſt and higheſt price (as Peter ſaith) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forthwith loue is poured abroad in our hearts, by the holy Ghoſt, whereby we are frée, chearfull, omnipotent, doers, workers, and conquerour of all tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſeruants of our neighbours, yet Lords of all things notwithſtanding. But ſuch as doe not know the gifts giuen vnto them through Chriſt, to them Chriſt is borne in vaine: ſuch wander in the way of works, and ſhall neuer attaine to the taſte and féeling of thoſe things. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as our neighbour is preſſed downe with neceſſity, and wanteth of our ſtore &amp; abundance, euen ſo were we ouerwhelmed with neceſſity in the ſight of God, and néeded altogether his mercy. Wherefore as our heauenly father did ſuccour vs in Chriſt Ieſu fréely, euen ſo ought wee
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:9429:49"/>
help our neighbour fréely by our body and by our workes, and euery of vs muſt be made a certaine Chriſt each to other, that wée may bee made debtours of Chriſt, and that Chriſt may bee one and the ſame in all, that is to ſay, that wée may be true Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Who is able therefore to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the riches and glory of a Chriſtian life, which is able to doe all things,<note place="margin">The glory of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian life.</note> poſſeſſeth all things, and néedeth nothing, an Empreſſe and Conquereſſe of ſinne, death, and hell, and withall an hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid neuertheleſſe, ſeruiceable and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to all? but the more is the pity. This Chriſtian Iuſtification is, at this day, altogether vnknowne in the whole world, neither is it preached, nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured, in ſo much, that we are our ſelues ignorant of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eir name, and for what cauſe we bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>éemed and called Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. True <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">In what reſpect we be named Chriſtians</note> wee haue receiued our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of Chriſt, not being abſent from vs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> dwelling within vs. That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s to ſay, whiles we beléeue in him, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ioyntly and mutually a certaine Chriſt
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:9429:50"/>
eche to other, applying our ſelues to our neighbours, euen as Chriſt hath giuen himſelfe to vs.</p>
            <p>But in theſe our dayes we are taught by mens doctrines to ſéeke after nought elſe but deſeruings, and merites, and the things which are our own, &amp; haue made of Chriſt nought elſe, but a ſharp Lawma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, much more auſtere than <hi>Moſes</hi> was.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The holy Mother of Chriſtian example of Faith. <hi>Luke</hi> 2.</note>Semblably, the bleſſed virgin <hi>Mary</hi> did exhibite her ſelfe a ſingular preſident of the Faith aboue al others, whiles after the manner of all other women ſhe was purified according to <hi>Moſes</hi> Law (as it is ſet down in the 2 of Luke) whereas being notwithſtanding not bound to any ſuch law, nor néeded to be purified in any ſuch wiſe, yet ſhe yéelded her ſelfe to the law of her own accord, and of a frée loue vnto the law, being made like vnto other women, leſt ſhée might ſeeme to offe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> or deſpiſe them. She was not therefore made righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous for that worke, but being righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous before, ſhee did this déed ſurely, and without coactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. In like maner ought our workes to be put in vre, not to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nd to
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:9429:50"/>
be iuſtified by them, for as much as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing iuſtified firſt by Faith, it behooueth vs to worke all things fréely and cheerefully for our neighbours ſake.</p>
            <p>So alſo Paul did circumciſe his ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler Timothy,<note place="margin">Paul doth teach workes.</note> not becauſe Timothy née<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be circumciſed vnto righteouſneſſe: but left hee might offend or deſpiſe the Iewes that were weake in Faith, and which as yet were not capable of the frée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Faith. But contrariwiſe, when as the Iewes did vrge a neceſſity to be cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſed to righteouſnes, ſetting at naught the fréedome of Faith, hee did withſtand them, and would not permit <hi>Titus</hi> to bee circumciſed, Galath. 3.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.</note> for as he would not willingly offend or contemne the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becillitie or weakeneſſe of others in the Faith, applying himſelfe to their capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for a time ſo likewiſe, would hee not giue place to the will of ſtiffenecked In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticiaries, when the liberty of Faith was like to ſuffer reproch, or be deſpiſed, kéeping the midway, bearing with the weake for a ſeaſon, and alwayes ſetting himſelfe againſt the indurate, to the end
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:9429:51"/>
he might conuert all in generality to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the liberty of Faith. With like af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection muſt our workes bee employed, that we tolerate the weaklings in Faith, as the Apoſtle teacheth in the <hi>14.</hi> to the Romanes, but that with courage wée reſiſt the inflexible vrgers of workes, of the which wee will treate more at large hereafter.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe Chriſt in the <hi>17.</hi> of Mathew, when tribute was demanded of his Diſciples,<note place="margin">An exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of our Lord Chriſt.</note> aſked the queſtion of Saint Peter, whether the children of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome were exempt from paying Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, and Peter affirming that they were, did command him notwithſtanding to goe to the Sea, ſpeaking theſe words, <hi>Leſt we giue them cauſe of offence, goe, and the Fiſh that firſt commeth to thy hands take, and opening his mouth, thou ſhalt finde a groate, take the ſame, and giue it for thee and me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This example is very much auaylea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for our purpoſe. In the which, Chriſt doth call himſelfe and his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples frée, and Kings ſonnes, which
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:9429:51"/>
ſtand in néede of nothing, and yet of his owne accord ſubmitteth himſelfe, and payeth Tribute.</p>
            <p>Therefore, by how much this worke of Chriſt was neceſſary to Chriſt, and profitable vnto righteouſneſſe and ſaluation, euen ſo much are all the workes of his elect and faithfull auailea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to righteouſneſſe, whereas they be all following after righteouſneſſe, and freely performed onely to the neceſſity and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of others.</p>
            <p>Of the ſame condition are the workes preſcribed by Paul in the thirtéenth Chapter to the Romanes,<note place="margin">Take hold of Luther all ye Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, and admit him to be your tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher.</note> and in the third to Timothy, <hi>That men ſhould bee ſubiect to the higher po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, and prepared to all good workes,</hi> not becauſe they ſhould bee iuſtified thereby, where as they bee righteous already through Faith, but that by theſe they might both bée ſubiect to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and to the higher powers, add of a frée loue yéelde humbly obedience to their will in the fréedome of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:9429:52"/>Of this ſame ſort ought the workes of all Colledges, Monaſteries, and Prieſtes haue béene employed, that euery of them might haue perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the workes of their profeſſion and eſtate to this end, that by theſe, euery of them might exerciſe not righteouſnes, but the taming of his owne body, yéel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereby example to others, who haue themſelues alſo néede to chaſtiſe their owne bodyes. Then alſo, that they might expreſſe humble obedience to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, applying themſelues to their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, of a frée loue, hauing neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe a ſpeciall regard alwaies to this onely, to witte, that through vaine confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, none of them preſume to be iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to merite, or to be ſaued by them, which thing is the proper and peculiar office o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Faith onely, as I haue often ſaid before.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of a true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</note>Therefore, who ſo were furniſhed wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this doctrine, might eaſily without dan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger wade in theſe infinite impoſitions an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> traditions of the Pope, of Biſhops, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>keries, of Churches, of Princes an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Magiſtrates, the which ſome fooliſh pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtors
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:9429:52"/>
doe ſo obtrude vpon vs, as though they were of an vnauoydable neceſſitie to bee performed, for the obtaining of righteouſneſſe and ſaluation, calling them commonly the iniunctions of the Church, being in déede nothing leſſe. For a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man may deba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e with himſelfe on this wiſe, I will faſt I will pray, I will apply my ſelfe to all whatſoeuer is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by men, not becauſe I need to doe any of theſe, to procure righteouſneſſe or ſaluation by them: but becauſe I will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe mine obedience herein to the Pope, to the Biſhops, to the Potentate, and to the Magiſtrate, or to my neighbour for example ſake, for this cauſe I will doe and ſuffer all things, euen as Chriſt did worke and ſuffer many greater things for my ſake, whereof he needed not to doe any one, being made for my ſake ſubiect vnto the law, when as in deede he was not vnder the law. And although theſe things be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted of me through the tyrannous force, and iniurious tyranny of the Magiſtrates, yet ſhall they be no preiudice to me, ſo lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g as they be not againſt the glory of God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:9429:53"/>The premiſſes conſidered, it is an eaſie matter for any man to iudge certainly:<note place="margin">The diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the good and the euill paſtors.</note> betwixt the difference of all works, and al lawes, &amp; know ſkilfully who be blind, and witleſſe Preachers, &amp; who be true &amp; faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full paſtors. For whatſoeuer worke bée not directed to this only marke, namely, to be employed to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chaſtiſme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body, or to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dutiful co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> neighbor (ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it enforce not any thing directly againſt Gods glory) ſurely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> work is neither good nor Chriſtianlike. And this is the cauſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I feare me much, very few Colledges at all, any Monaſteries, Altars, or any Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical exerciſes at this day, be not tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Chriſtian, &amp; that alſo as well thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per &amp; peculiar faſtings, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> petty prayers to certain Saints be not Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I feare me much (I ſay) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in al theſe things regard is had of nought elſe, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth to our ſelues, whiles we be thus minded, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by meanes of theſe exerciſes, our ſins are cleanſed, &amp; ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> obtained ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, &amp; ſo Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> liberty is ouerthrowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the cauſe wherof procedeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> blind ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faith, full of al fréedome.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:9429:53"/>
Which groſſe ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; ſuppreſſion of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, very many blind &amp; buſſardly paſtors doe earneſtly maintaine, whileſt they doe gréedily perſwade, &amp; vrge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people to ſuch exerciſes, adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cing them aboue Moone and Stars, &amp; glorifying the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with their pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, but of faith neuer vttering ſo much as one word. But I wold wiſh thée to be wel ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed, that if thou haue wil at any time to pray, to faſt,<note place="margin">Good ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice.</note> or to found Churches (as they tearme it) to beware thou do not this to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end to procure to thy ſelf any te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modity therwith: for in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, thou ſhalt be preiudiciall to thy faith, which only doth miniſter all things vnto thée,<note place="margin">Only faith muſt be attended vnto.</note> &amp; therfore ought only be attended vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it may be encreaſed, whether it be oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied in workes, or exerciſed with affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: but giue fréely without hope of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitall, whatſoeuer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> giueſt, that others may be reléeued, and grow in well doing through thée, and thy liberality, for this is the way to make thée a good and a true Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man. For what ſhall auaile thée, thy goods, &amp; thy works, whereof thou art endued with a ſurplus, ouer and beſides
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:9429:54"/>
thoſe which do ſerue to the neceſſary cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſement of the body? when as thou art ſufficiently enriched for thy neceſſities, through the Faith, in the which God hath endued thée with all plentifull ſtore.</p>
            <p>Behold, by this rule it behooueth vs to poure out each vpon other, and to make common each vnto other the goods which we haue receiued of God, and that every man cloath himſelfe with his neighbours eſtate, and ſo apply himſelfe to his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours neceſſities, euen as if wee were in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like neceſſity our ſelues:<note place="margin">A rule touching brotherly loue.</note> out of Chriſts ſtorehouſe they ouerflowed, and from him ſlow daily vnto vs, who hath ſo tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n our neceſſities vpon himſelfe, and ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed all things for our ſakes, as if himſelfe had béene the ſame that wee be. They flow likewiſe from vs, vnto them who ſtand in need of them, in ſo much, that I am bound to poure out before God my faith, and my righteouſneſſe, to couer and entreat for the ſinnes of my neighbour, the burthen of whoſe ſinnes I muſt in mine owne perſon ſuſtaine, and ſo trauell and bee afflicted in them, as if
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:9429:54"/>
they were mine owne ſinnes, for on this wiſe was Chriſt afflicted for our ſakes, for this is the very true loue, this is the rule of a pure Chriſtian loue, which is in them very naturall and pure indéed, in whom dwelleth a pure and ſincere Faith indéed, whereupon, the Apoſtle in the firſt to the Corinthians, the thirtéenth Chapter, doth giue this ſingular prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue to loue, <hi>That it ſeeketh not the things that are her owne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore we doe conclude, that a Chriſtian man doth not liue in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but in Chriſt,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. A Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an man doth liue in himſelf, and in his neighbour</note> and in his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, or that to be a Chriſtian man, is to dwell in Chriſt by Faith, and in his neighbour by loue.</p>
            <p>Againe, a Chriſtian man is raiſed vp aboue himſelfe to Godward by Faith, and is throwne downe beneath himſelfe, toward his neighbour by loue, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling alwayes neuertheleſſe in God, and in the loue of God, according to the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt in the firſt of Iohn, <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, verily, I ſay vnto you, from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foorth you ſhall ſee the heauens opened,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:9429:55"/>
and the Angels of God aſcending and deſcending vpon the ſonne of man.</hi> And thus farre ſufficiently concerning Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian liberty, which is (as you ſée) ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and true, making our hearts frée from all ſinnes, from all lawes, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements (as Paul witneſſeth in his firſt Epiſtle to Timothy, the firſt Chapter, <hi>The Law was not made for the iuſt man</hi>) which liberty doth as farre ſurmount all other outward and external liberties in excellencie, as the Heauens doth ſurpaſſe the Earth, which Chriſt grant vs to vnderſtand, and enioy to our comfort, Amen.</p>
            <p>In fine, to ſatiſfie thoſe perſons, who can neuer heare any thing, be it neuer ſo well ſpoken, but that they will depraue it by euill conceiuing, ſomewhat muſt bee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed, if that at the leaſt they be able to conceiue the ſame.<note place="margin">Againſt the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the fleſh.</note> There be very many, who hearing the doctrine of this Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an liberty of Faith, will by and by take occaſion thereof, to maintaine the liberty of the fleſh, ſuppoſing forthwith that they may lawfully attempt all things, nor
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:9429:55"/>
will expreſſe their liberty and Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in any one thing elſe, than in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing, and reprouing of Ceremonies, of mens traditions and conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as though they ought for this cauſe to bée déemed Chriſtians, becauſe they doe not faſt in the dayes appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for faſting, or becauſe they eate fleſh, whyleſt other doe abſtaine from fleſh, or becauſe they doe not fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Maſſes and Mattene, or other vſuall ſeruice in the Church, diſdainefully ſcorning and ſcoffing at the ordinances of men, vtterly ſetting at naught all other things appertaining to Chriſtian Religion. Againſt whom,<note place="margin">Againſt the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in workes.</note> there is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſort that doe with tooth and nayle bend their force, which contrariwiſe, doe endeauour to attayne ſaluation, by the onely obſeruation and reuerence of Ceremonies, as though they ſhould for this cauſe be ſaued, becauſe they faſt on the faſting dayes, or abſtaine from fleſh, or inure themſelues to certaine prayers, exceſſiuely vaunting the traditions of the Church, and of the fathers, yet otherwiſe
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:9429:56"/>
not eſtéeming the things that are proper and peculiar to our Chriſtian Faith, worth a ruſh, both which ſorts of people are ſurely altogether much blame-worthy for as much, as paſſing ouer matters of great importance, and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly neglecting the things neceſſarily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to ſaluation, they turmoyle them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in ſo great outrage about thoſe trifling toyes, being altogether vnneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary and vnprofitable.</p>
            <p>How much more ſoundly doth Paul teach to kéepe the midde way, condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning both thoſe by pathes, ſaying, <hi>He that eateth, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t him not deſpiſe him that eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not: and he that eateth not, let him not iudge him that eateth.</hi> Héere you ſée, that ſuch as do neglect, and condemne the ceremonies, not of deuotion, but of mere contempt, bee accompted blame-worthy, whereas the Apoſtle teacheth them not to deſpiſe, for knowledge doth cauſe to ſwell, and to be puft vp. Againe, he exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the obſtinate, that they iudge not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, for neither of them doth obſerue charity, edifying one another, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:9429:56"/>
in this perplexity, councell muſt bee ſought out of Scripture, which doth teach vs, not to decline on the right, nor on the left hand, but to enſue the right iudgements of the Lord, quickning the hearts: for as no man is righteous, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hée humbleth himſelfe, and is addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to works, and rites of ceremonies, ſo neither ſhall any man hee accompted for this only cauſe righteous, becauſe he doth omit and contemne them.</p>
            <p>For wee bée not freed through our Faith in Chriſt from workes, but from the opinions of workes, that is to ſay, from the fooliſh preſumption con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued of Iuſtification, purchaſed by meanes of workes: for Faith doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déeme our conſciences, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>erly kéepe and preſerue the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, wherby we attaine this knowledge, that righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe conſiſteth not in workes, albeit workes neither can, nor ought to bee neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected As wee cannot liue to this world without food and ſuſtenance, nor with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the generall preſeruation of this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall body, yet is not our righteouſneſſe
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:9429:57"/>
ſelled in theſe, but in Faith, for the which, the other things notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding may not bee deſpiſed, and vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhaken off. So in this world, wée bée faſt chayned to the neceſſary preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the life of this body, yet are wée not thereby made righteous, <hi>My kingdome</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>is not from hence, nor of this World,</hi> but hee ſaid not, my kingdome is not héere, nor in this world. Likewiſe Paul, <hi>Albeit wee walke in the fleſh, yet our warfare is not according to the fleſh.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.</note> And in the firſt to the Galathians, <hi>Whereas I doe liue in the fleſh, I liue in the faith of the ſonne of God.</hi> Euen ſo in this that we worke that we liue, and that we are exerciſed in workes and ceremonies, the neceſſity of this preſent life,<note place="margin">How we ought to deale with the obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate.</note> and the carefull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of gouerning our bodies, doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act it of vs, yet are wee neuer a deale righteous by them, but in the Faith of the Sonne of God. Therefore, a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man muſt kéepe his courſe in the midde way, and muſt paſſe away from thoſe two ſorts of people, for either
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:9429:57"/>
hee ſhall méet with thoſe peruerſe fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes, being indurate with theſe Ceremonies, which, like deafe Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents,<note place="margin">Aſpides:</note> will not hearken vnto the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the truth, but magnifie their Ceremonies, command and enforce the obſeruation of them without Faith, as neceſſities of Iuſtification, ſuch as the Iewes were in times paſt vnwilling to come to knowledge thereby, to walke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right. Such behooueth vs to reſiſt, to impugne them, and to offend them ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, leſt by this their wicked opinion, they draw together with themſelues ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, into their falſe illuſions. In the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of ſuch it is conuenient to eat fleſh, to breake faſting dayes, and for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of our liberty in faith, to do other like things, which they reckon in place of moſt gréeuous ſinnes. And in this manner muſt wee ſpeake of them, <hi>Let them alone, they bee blinde themſelues, and blinde guides of the blinde,</hi> for in this reſpect Paul would not ſuffer Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:9429:58"/>
to receiue Circumciſion, though they ſtiffely vrged hereunto. So did Chriſt alſo defend his Apoſtles, when as they pluckt the eares of corne on the Sabboth day, and many ſuch like.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</note>On the other ſide, we ſhal méet with the ſimple, vnlearned, ignorant, and weake in Faith (as Paul calleth them) whoſe capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities are not yet able to comprehend this libertie of Faith, though they haue a will thereunto. Such muſt be borne withall, leſt they be offended: and their weakneſſe muſt be fauoured, vntill they may be more fully inſtructed. For whereas thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons do not obſerue ſuch ceremonies of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny grounded malice, nor are wilfully ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate in iudgement, but conceiue of them according to the imbecility of their Faith onely, faſtings, abſtinence from choice meates, and ſuch other ceremonies, which they doe ſuppoſe to be neceſſary, muſt be obſerued for auoyding offence in them. For this doth Charitie exact of vs, which hurteth no man but helpes vs. For ſuch
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:9429:58"/>
continue not weaklings through their owne default, but through the negligence of their paſtors, which with their cramps and grapling yrons of traditions, haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled euil handled, and deadly wounded them, who otherwiſe ought to haue béene deliuered, made whole, and reuiued with the doctrine of Faith and Chriſtian Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. The ſame doth the Apoſtle teach in the fourteenth Chapter to the Rom. <hi>If my meate doe offend my brother,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>I will not eate fleſh for euer.</hi> And againe, <hi>I know that in Chriſt there is nothing defiled, but vnto him that thinketh it to bee defiled, but it is euill to the man that eateth to the offence of his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore,<note place="margin">Againſt the lawes and law-makers.</note> although wee muſt ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly withſtand thoſe teachers of Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſharpely inueigh againſt the conſtitutions of Biſhops, wherewith they ouerrunne the people of God, yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard muſt be had of the timorous weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, whom thoſe cruell bloudſuckers,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:9429:59"/>
doe cruelly detaine captiue with thoſe tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, vntill they be ſet at liberty. On this wiſe encounter manfully againſt the Wolues, but for the Shéepe, and not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Shéepe alſo, which thou ſhalt the better do, if thou bend thy force earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt thoſe Lawes and Lawmakers, and yet withall thy ſelfe obſerue them in the ſight of the weake, leſt they become offended through thée, vntill themſelues may know that Tyranny, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand their owne liberties. And if thou wilt enioy thine owne liberty, vſe it to thy ſelfe in ſecret (as Paul teacheth thée in the fourtéenth to the Rom.) <hi>Keep thou the Faith which thou haſt vnto thy ſelfe before God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>but beware that thou vſe it not before the weake.</hi> Againe, <hi>before Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants and obſtinate frowards, vſe the ſame in deſpight of them, yea, and that moſt manfully and conſtantly: That they alſo may vnderſtand their owne wickedneſſe,</hi> and their Lawes to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing auaileable to righteouſneſſe, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:9429:59"/>
that they had no authority to make ſuch lawes.</p>
            <p>For as much therefore,<note place="margin">To the yong in yeares.</note> as the ſociety of this preſent life cannot be maintained in due order without ceremonies &amp; workes: Yea rather, foraſmuch as the raging and rude age of yong perſons hath néede to be reſtrained and bridled with ſuch raines, as it were with a Snaffle, and that euery man ought to chaſtiſe his own body: with the ſame exerciſes, it behoueth therefore the Miniſter of Chriſt to be prudent and faithfull, that hee may ſo inſtruct and guide Chriſts flocke in all theſe things, that their Conſcience and Faith may not be offended, and to be circumſpect, that no vnſauorie opinion, nor bitter ſmatch of loathſomneſſe may take roote in them, by meanes whereof, many may be infected, (wherof Paul did forewarne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Hebrues) that is to ſay, leſt looſing their faith vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly, they beginne to be defiled with vaine preſumption of workes, as though they were to bee ſaued by workes, which is a
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:9429:60"/>
ſpéedy contagion, and doth pierce déeply into many, vnleſſe faith bee buſily and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly enforced withall, but the diſeaſe is vnauoydable, where faith being put vp to ſilence, onely traditions of men taught to bee retayned, as hath béene hitherto through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peſtiferous, deteſtable, &amp; ſoule-ſlaying traditions of our Prelates, and vagarant opinions of our Diuines, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling infinite ſoules to the Deuill, with theſe intricate fetters, which by plaine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration doth denounce very Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Danger in the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</note>To conclude, ſuch as is pouerty in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance, painfulneſſe in authority, humbleneſſe in honour, abſtinence in fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, chaſtity in valliance, euen ſo righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of faith is dangerouſly beſet being ioined with ceremonies: <hi>May a man carry fire in his boſome</hi> (ſaith Salomon) <hi>and not burne his garments?</hi> And yet as in riches, in authority, in honours, in dalliance, in banquetings, ſo muſt we be conuerſant in ceremonies, that is to
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:9429:60"/>
ſay, in dangers: yea rather as it is néed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for yong boyes to be nurſed and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed in the laps and armes of maydens, leſt they periſh, in whom being growne to riper yeares, were no ſmall perill of ſafety to frequent the company of may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens: Euen ſo is it requiſite to lock vp y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ranging yéeres of licencious youth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Cloyſters, yea, within iron cloſſets of ſuch ceremonies and exerciſes, whereas they may bee reſtrained and abide corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, leſt their inſolent courage draw them headlong into wickedneſſe. Which ceremonies do neuertheles procure death vnto them, if they perſeuere in opinion to bee iuſtifiable by them, whereas they ought rather to bee inſtructed, that they were clogged with ſuch reſtraint, not for any ſuch cauſe as to bee made righteous, or to merit much thereby, but to the end, they ſhould not ruſh wilfully into vices, and ſo bee the more tractable trained to the righteouſneſſe of faith: which they
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:9429:61"/>
would in no wiſe endure through the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of their youth, vnleſſe the ſame had béene tamed and brought low.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of what eſtimation ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies be.</note>Which doth argue, that ceremonies ought not to be of any other price and eſtimation in the life of a true Chriſtian man, than as amongſt Carpenters and Artificers, certaine old poſtes, logges, or platformes, are framed to direct &amp; raiſe vp buildings by: which bee not made to the end they ſhould ſerue and remaine to any ſpeciall vſe, but becauſe without ſuch by-helpes, buildings and workes cannot eaſily bee rayſed, for when the work or building is finiſhed, thoſe deuiſes are laid aſide.</p>
            <p>So that here you ſée, that ceremonies are not vtterly abrogated, but rather earneſtly required, but the vaine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion and preſumption of them is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned, becauſe no man accompteth them to be a true and permanent building. If any man would bee ſo notably
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:9429:61"/>
ſenſeleſſe, as to regard nothing elſe in his whole life, but to direct thoſe preparatiues, with all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, with all diligence, with all continuance, and would neuer bende his cogitations to the very building it ſelfe, ſtroking, ſmoothing, and vaunting himſelfe in theſe preparatiues, and vaine rotten proppes, would not all men lament his madneſſe, and thinke within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, that whiles he employed this coſt to no purpoſe, he might haue builded ſome matter of better ſubſtance? So now we do neither abando<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ceremonies, nor works, but rather doe allow them, neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe we doe vtterly abhorre the vaine o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion conceiued of them, leſt that any man perſwade himſelfe, that to obſerue them is the true righteouſneſſe, as Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites doe, which doe abuſe and miſpend their whole life in theſe exerciſes, &amp; neuer reach vnto the ſubſtance, in reſpect where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they are practized, or as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth: <hi>Alwayes learning, and neuer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:9429:62"/>
to the knowledge of the Truth:</hi> For they ſéeme as though they had a will to build, and alwayes prepare themſelues thereunto, and yet they neuer build, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting alwaies in the glittering ſhadow of godlineſſe, but neuer attaine to the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and ſubſtance thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Againſt them that be nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious.</note>Yet do they wonderfully flatter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in theſe exerciſes, preſuming alſo arrogantly to iudge all others, whom they ſée not glittering in the like brauery of workes, whereas they might otherwiſe bee able to atchieue matters of greater importance, to the ſingular comfort of themſelues and others, with this vainely imployed oſtentation, and abuſe of Gods gifts, if they were indued with a right and true faith. But whereas the nature of man and reaſon (as they tearme it) na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, is naturally inclined to ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and purſuing all Lawes and works, is proue of herſelfe to fall into vaine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of obtaining iuſtification through
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:9429:62"/>
them: adde moreouer herevnto, becauſe it is accuſtomed and inured to conceiue ſo highly of the ſame workes, through the vſuall admiration of all earthly law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers, it is not poſſible ſurely of her owne ſtrength, to cleare it ſelfe from this ſeruile bondage of workes, and to bend her force to know the liberty of faith.</p>
            <p>Therefore it is requiſite,<note place="margin">From whence the law of wiſdome doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede.</note> that we flée to prayer, that the Lord would vouchſafe to draw vs and make vs inſtructed vnto GOD, that is to ſay, apt Schollers for God, and that himſelfe will vouchſafe to write his Law in our hearts (as hee hath promiſed) otherwiſe we doe all come to confuſion. For except he doe engraffe in our ſoules this maruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Wiſdome hidden in a myſtery, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture cannot chooſe but condemne it, and adiudge it for an Heretique, becauſe ſhée is offended <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and appeareth fooliſh in her eyes. Euen as we ſaw to haue hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:9429:63"/>
in times paſt to the Prophets of GOD and the Apoſtles, and euen as the wicked blinde Prelates, and their falſe flatterers doe now vnto mee, and others like vnto mée, vnto whom, and to vs alſo, GOD bee mercifull, and ſhew the light of his countenance vpon vs, that wee may know his way vpon the earth, and his ſauing health amongſt all generations. Who be bleſſed for euer and euer.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:9429:63"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
